<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A joco-serious discourse in two dialogues between a Northumberland-gentleman and his tenant, a Scotchman, both old cavaliers : with an anagram prefixt to them : being some miscellaneous essays written upon several occasions / by George Stuart.</title>
            <author>Stuart, George.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1686</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 190 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61863</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S6026</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10936</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13295831</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13295831</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98884</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61863)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98884)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 439:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A joco-serious discourse in two dialogues between a Northumberland-gentleman and his tenant, a Scotchman, both old cavaliers : with an anagram prefixt to them : being some miscellaneous essays written upon several occasions / by George Stuart.</title>
                  <author>Stuart, George.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 76 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Benjamin Tooke ... and John Story ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1686.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse, including music and songs.</note>
                  <note>"Licensed, June 12th, 1686. Rob. Midgley"</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98884:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98884:1"/>
            <p>A <hi>JOCO-SERIO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> DISCOURSE. IN TWO DIALOGUES, BETWEEN A <hi>Northumberland</hi>-Gentleman, AND HIS Tenant a <hi>Scotchman,</hi> Both old <hi>CAVALIERS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With an <hi>ANAGRAM</hi> prefixt to them: BEING Some Miſcellaneous Eſſays, Written upon ſeveral Occaſions.</p>
            <p>By <hi>GEORGE ST<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ART.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Omne tulit punctum, qui miſcuit utile dulci.</hi>
            </q>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>LICENSED,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>June</hi> 12th. 1686.</date>
                     </dateline> 
                     <signed>Rob. Midgley.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Benjamin Tooke,</hi> at the <hi>Ship</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-Yard,</hi> and <hi>John Story,</hi> in <hi>New-Caſtle,</hi> 1686.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="modern_bookplate">
            <pb facs="tcp:98884:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:98884:2"/>
            <head>TO Sir <hi>HENRY BRABANT</hi> Knight, MAYOR OF NEW-CASTLE UPON TINE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF theſe following Sheets had been deſigned to have gratifi'd a particular Humor, or private Intereſt, it had behov'd me to have made this Dedication to one, of whoſe Perſonal Acquaintance I were more happy in, than I am of yours; but ſince the raſhneſs of my Fancy has ſuggeſted a more pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
<pb facs="tcp:98884:3"/>concern, I know none more fit to protect my good Wiſhes to that Royal Cauſe, which you have ſo vigorouſly aſſerted than your ſelf: Or if it had been poſſible for me (as I thank God it is not) to have offer'd an Effort, which by any Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence might appear prejudicial to our Soveraign Lord the King, and conſequently, to the Univerſal Well-fare of all his Subjects; it had been but Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in me, to have conceal'd ſuch an ungodly At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt from you; for what Incouragement cou'd any diſorderly Act (if there were no worſe in't) expect from a Loyaliſt of your Size, whom Malice it ſelf cannot feign ev'r to have trode one wry ſtep in the Duty of a Loyal Subject, and Office of a diſcreet Magiſtrate?</p>
            <p>But why, Sir, ſhould I pretend to be a Stranger to you? Has not the whole Courſe of your Life, (ev'n when Iniquity skrew'd it ſelf up into the Seat of <hi>Lord Paramount</hi>) render'd you ſufficiently conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous? firſt, to all true Lovers of your three ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive Royal Maſters, and next to the Adverſe Party? Did not thoſe ſet you before their wary Eyes, as a perfect Pattern both of Courage and
<pb facs="tcp:98884:3"/>Obedience, and theſe, as the very Butt of their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable Malice? Cou'd I live ſo long near you, as I have done, and be unacquainted with your great Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits? No Sir, it's impoſſible, tho this be the firſt time I've given you the trouble of an Addreſs.</p>
            <p>It was in that Critical Juncture, you did manifeſt the true Senſe of your Soul; when your early En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to cruſh the Cockatrice in the ſhell, did but predict the After-acts of your Life to be no more to you, but drawing your own Breath.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Satan,</hi> among the reſt of his ſubtile and hectoring Artifices, had the Impudence to tell his ineffable Creator, that <hi>JOB ſerv'd not God for nothing;</hi> yet for all this, when he had got him in his power, and deveſted him of all that was dear to Fleſh and Blood, this admirable piece of Piety was ſtill the ſame. And pray you, Sir, what have all thoſe dreadful Engines prevail'd, which have inceſſantly batter'd againſt you from your Cradle? (And I wiſh the plentiful Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of Youthful Blood, or the unavoidable De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cays of old Age, cou'd but obtain a Writ of Eaſe) what have they prevail'd I ſay? Nothing, but to your Advantage: The more they ſtrip't, you did but
<pb facs="tcp:98884:4"/>the fairlyer diſcover a ſpotleſs and active Soul, dart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſelf thorow, and ſpringing in the exact and liv'ly Lineaments of a well Organiz'd Body; or made you appear like the Winter Sun, which ſhines brighteſt, when the Froſt is moſt nipping,</p>
            <p>Again, Sir, the Magnanimous <hi>St. Paul</hi> did freely undergo Impriſonments, was over and over again, whip't by the <hi>Jews,</hi> beaten with Rods, Shipwrack't, was in Perils of Water, in Perils of Robbers, in Perils of his own Country-men, in Perils among the Heathens, in Perils in the City, in Perils in the Wilderneſs, in Perils in the Sea, but the worſt of all was Perils among <hi>falſe Brethren;</hi> and yet this reſolute <hi>Hero</hi> ſtood unſhaken to the very laſt. If I were but to trace the Compariſon upon your account (as far as the Caſes run Parallel) it were but ſuperfluous to thoſe that know you, and incredible to ſuch as do not. As long as Vice is Vice, it will ſtand in Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to Vertue; and while there is good Men to ſuffer, there will be ill Men to perſecute. I dare not ſay <hi>behold the End of theſe,</hi> for who knows but Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, out of the inexhauſtible Treaſure of his Bounty, may in good time give a better Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding;
<pb facs="tcp:98884:4"/>but if ſome of their Beginnings have not been Ominous, it's a Paradox to more than my ſelf; and let ſuch as diſtruſt this, look back on thoſe who have formerly imbarqu't themſelves in ſuch rotten, and leaking Veſſels and if they cannot diſcern a palpable Fatality attending the runners of ſuch Riſques, I hope they'll give quicker-ſighted Perſons leave to won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at their Blindneſs.</p>
            <p>I will be very thankful to any of your Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies (of which by the Inſtigation of the Devil, and his Deareſt Daughter the <hi>Good old Cauſe</hi> yo've had a gay convenient Number) if any of 'em, I ſay, can ſhew me when ever a force-putt-<hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſt</hi> became not (as ſoon as ev'r he met with a promiſing Game for't) the moſt Voracious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourer of that ſacred Authority, which he moſt ſolemnly ſwore to defend: But it's Hypocriſy, not Converſion which I diſclaim; and what Precaution is herein to be uſed, falls under the Cognizance of our Superiours.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:98884:5"/>
            <p>Sir, It's not the hollow ſound of an empty Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negyrick can Eccho to your Character. Original Worth is the firmeſt <hi>Baſis</hi> of true Virtue: And in order to that, your own Acts can beſt ſpeak you: It only remains that I beg Pardon for this Freedom, and the Honour to be allow'd to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe my ſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Loyal Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt humble, and Obedient Servant, George Stuart.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:98884:5"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE, IN A DIALOGUE, BETWEEN THE AUTHOR, AND THE CENSORIOUS READER.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Author.</speaker>
               <p>HERE now,—at laſt ye may tak't.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Reader.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why ſo ſurly pray'e? Other Authors will call me Courteous Reader,—Gentle-Reader.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Author.</speaker>
               <p>Tho' perhaps thou haſt play'd a hundred skittiſh Tricks in thy time.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Reader.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And then they'll ſay, I intreat you to take my weak Endeavours in good part, and I ſhall hereafter be incourag'd to,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:98884:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Author,</speaker>
               <p>Ay marry, weak enough in all Conſcience; but tak't <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thow wilt, if e'er thou get'ſt any more of me, it ſhall ſpeak to thee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Reader.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But what is't all this while—? Let me ſee,—Ho, is't time aday now to publiſh any Poem upon ſuch</hi> Subjects?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Author<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> Why not? They were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> firſt (if a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> had been well to that) as early ſtarted (and ſome Hundreds can bear me Witneſs of it) as any that appeal'd upon thoſe ſcores: Howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, they being only then occaſionally introduc'd, I doubt not but the Deſign, in the mai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, will prove re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſhing enough to a Loyal Palate at any time; and for ſuch as are not, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>m not ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>rry <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not pleaſe them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Reader.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Unriddle that?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Author.</speaker>
               <p>I was at <hi>New-Caſtle</hi> upon <hi>Tine (Feb. 11<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1684/5.)</hi> when the doleful News of the Death (if ſuch can be ſaid to dye) of the beſt, and one of the greateſt Monarchs upon Earth firſt filled that Place with Lamentation. All appear'd in a Sorrow ſuitable to the great Cauſe the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. Immediately, they Proclaim'd our preſent dread Soveraign, (upon whom Heav'n ſhower down the choiceſt of his Bleſſings) ſolemniſing his wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Acceſs to the Imperial Crowns of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Royal Anceſtors, with magnificent Splendour: Their New <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> was to come in the next day, but one, after; and to Illuiſtrate the Royal Goddneſs in ſo ample a Grant, another ſtately Preparation of the ſame ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>p was ſet a Foot. Having for that while ſequeſtred my ſelf from all Buſineſs, reſolving to ſee the far end of it, the Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to all of a ſudden ſtruck. I had but little time, and ſo I task't myſelf ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, and got what I intended long enough ready, before their
<pb facs="tcp:98884:6"/>Charter came in (which was upon the <hi>13th.</hi> as above.)</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Reader.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now I remember ſomething of it; and if I have not been miſinformed, the Entertainment that both it, and you for its ſake, met withall, from the Perſon you preſented it to, that day, might have ſufficiently cool'd your Fancy, and put a Period to any more Dialogues of that Nature.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Author.</speaker>
               <p>Quito contrary: For I nev'r had thought of a Second Dialogue, till the Firſt was ſo treated; for, I being a meer Stranger to all of Remark then preſent, followed the Common vogue; nor am I ſo skittiſh as to boggle at an Affront neither, for thanks to many of my good Neighbours, I'm well enough inured to that and all upon Equivalent Grounds: But one Swallow makes no Summer; and ſince no Body knows who we mean on, all's well enough. After I had ſmell'd the Rat, I changed not the Humor, but the Scene, and fitted ſome Conceits as well as I could for <hi>Durham,</hi> againſt the Coronation; having more time for't, I Lancht further our; the <hi>Landlord</hi> Aſſigns (as you'll find) moſt part of the Diſcourſe to the <hi>Tenant,</hi> and he in a Burleſquing way (after the <hi>Scotch</hi> manner) glances upon the Hiſtory of the laſt Seaven or Eight years, in Allegories fit for his Character; for, notwithſtanding the diſmal Tragedies (the tremendous Effects of Phanatical Fury) partly perpetrated, but more chiefly deſigned for the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Stage in that particle of time, there was yet room enough for a Drol. I communicated both Dialogues to not a few of my Acquaintances, all Perſons of indiſputable Integrity, and truly they had the good Fortune, at leaſt, not to be Contemn'd. They were ſomewhat noiſed abroad, and I was ſore put to it for peruſals, readings over, or, which was harder, giving Copies, that my time was ſpent to
<pb facs="tcp:98884:7"/>my prejudice: And further, ſuch Copies as I gave were Re-copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed 'till (beſides crippling the Verſes, and other Faults) they made the <hi>Tenant</hi> ſpeak like a <hi>Gew-gaw.</hi> I was unwilling to anſwer for any Fault but my owns; ſo, I ſent both to <hi>London</hi> to be Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about the beginning of <hi>June 1685.</hi> If the Act for Licenſing was then Revived, it was more then I knew: Therefore, to make ſure work, I truſted them in the Hands of a very Judicious and Ingenious Gentleman there, to know whether they contained any thing offenſive to the Publick, or diſguſtful to any Loyal Perſon. The unnatural Rebellion of the <hi>Weſt</hi> being then in the <hi>Zenith,</hi> he was taken up in higher matters, and they lay by him forgot 'till <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember</hi> next after. I met with a good report of this Gentleman, who got them Printed; I impowered him to receive them, and get them Licenſed and Printed, if it would turn to his Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage: After he had peruſed them, he returned them (with thanks tho I ſay it) aſſuring me the <hi>Tenants</hi> Language would prove inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable in the Southern parts, beſides, the Characters of ſeveral Perſons were ſo darkiſh, that they would ſcarce be apprehended. I now reckoned my ſelf at eaſe, but it was returned upon me, by ſuch as preſt me for Printed Copies, as a Contrivance of mine to avoid appearing in Print; (a vanity I never was fond of.) In Concluſion, I had ſuch profers to take the charge off my Hand, that he muſt have been worſe conditioned than I deſired to be repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that would have refuſed a Complyance. And a little after <hi>Chriſt-maſs</hi> I fell on and drew another draught, ſomethings I o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, others I alter'd, and a little I added, as alſo, the common <hi>Engliſh</hi> of every uncouth <hi>Scotch</hi> word, with ſome explicatory Notes on the Margent, thereby to facilitate the Characters, and render the <hi>Tenants</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:98884:7"/>Language intelligible. I know it's not uſual in Poems of this Nature, but if the Reader ſhould have both the Speech, and the Meaning of it to ſtudy, it might prove ſo Slaviſh, as to rebate the little piece of ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, he might otherways have.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Reader.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Here has been a great deal a do about nought, it ſeems.</hi> But why ſhou'd you Characterize thoſe Perſons, who have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſmarted under the ſevere Pens of the Greateſt Wits of the Nation?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Author.</speaker>
               <p>All of them have not, nor any in this manner; that ev'r I met with. Do but obſerve I pray'e now, If any Angler ſhou'd uſe allways the ſame Bait, or dubbing with his Hook, without reſpect to the Seaſon of the year, quality of the Water, diſpoſition of the Air, or Nature of Fiſhes be Angles for, he might oft return with an empty Panyer. One Mans Meat is another Mans Poyſon; and it's hard damning of Proverbs; Beſides all this, Loſers may beg leave to ſpeak.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Reader.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But let me look a little further into it. Why ſo great a diſtance betwixt the Natures of their diſcourſes in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places? Is that ſutable?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Author.</speaker>
               <p>If you will but (as I do) underſtand by the <hi>Landlord,</hi> and <hi>Tenant,</hi> the ſeveral degrees of all his Majeſty's Subjects, you'll find no greater Diſcrepancy in that, then may be in their other Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, and Accoutrements. As for example, the <hi>Landlord</hi> may ride on a Fourty-Pound Horſe, and the <hi>Tenant</hi> on a Fourty-Sinl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Galloway, and notwithſtanding, both Travel in the ſame Road.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Reader.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Have not you, in many places belyed the</hi> Tenants <hi>Speech, as</hi> lig, ſyke, Pſe, <hi>&amp;c.? Theſe, and many others being no</hi> Scotch <hi>words!</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Author.</speaker>
               <p>You muſt conſider the <hi>Tenant</hi> has liv'd long in <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberland,</hi> and has ſomewhat mixt his Dialect with the Native
<pb facs="tcp:98884:8"/>Inhabitants: The difference is ſmall, yet Dialogues ought to be natural, as alſo he will now and then drop a word or two right <hi>Engliſh</hi> for fine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; And in truth there's nothing more frequent among ſuch, when they ſpeak to any P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap> of Quality.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Reader.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why have you order'd thoſe few Songs, for the moſt part to old and Common Tunes?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Author.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe <hi>I</hi> would have them readily Sung. I have known ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Witty and Loyal Songs loſt, before Country People have found their Times. If any man think 'em worth newer, let him uſe his Art, and Welcom.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Reader.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is this the</hi> Scotch <hi>ſpelling in many of your common words (as</hi> geud <hi>for good,</hi> bloud <hi>for</hi> blood, Naig <hi>for Nag, &amp;c.</hi>)</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Author.</speaker>
               <p>No. There is no difference between the <hi>Scotſh</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſpelling; it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es in the pronouncing of 'em: And I have ſo letterd them, and all ſuch, only to put the <hi>Scotch</hi> way of it, into the <hi>Engliſh</hi> mans mouth; a Contrivance the Engliſh Poets are extraording<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry faulty in, nor can their way either touch our Idioms or Accent.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Reader.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But tell me this I prithee now?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Author.</speaker>
               <p>I'll tell thee no more, Man. The Preface is too long all-ready: Farewell.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:98884:8"/>
            <head>
               <hi>James Stuart,</hi> Second &amp; Seaventh. <hi>ANAGRAM.</hi> Juſt Man on Earth, uſed Sea, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>THE Labour's loſt, mangle not this Sacred name,</l>
               <l>For every Letter here's an <hi>Anagram.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The juſteſt Man on Earth, him Heav'ns allow,</l>
               <l>Juſtice requires that we to's Scepter bow.</l>
               <l>Such happineſs (be thankful) prov's we are</l>
               <l>'Pointed by God, for his peculiar care.</l>
               <l>He uſed Sea, there vigorouſly maintain'd</l>
               <l>Our Intereſt, and his own Glory gain'd.</l>
               <l>How cou'd he fail, when ſuch Auſpicious Gales</l>
               <l>(Ev'n Angel-breath) breez'd on his proſp'rous Sails?</l>
               <l>The Bulwark of his Country, King and Laws:</l>
               <l>Nothing cou'd match his Courage, but his Cauſe.</l>
               <l>By Prudent Conduct, Valour, Wiſe Command,</l>
               <l>Vanquiſh't our Foes at Sea, our Hearts at Land,</l>
               <l>They Trembling ſink; while we Triumphing ſtand.</l>
               <l>They yield their Weapons, and we give our Hearts;</l>
               <l>All ſtoop to him, ſubdu'd by diff'rent Arts.</l>
               <l>Why not ſubmit? Sure no Objection, where</l>
               <l>There's Lawful Conqueror, and Rightful Heir.</l>
               <l>Sir, proſtrate at your Princely Feet we lay</l>
               <l>Our Lives, our Fortunes, our <hi>et caetera.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:98884:9"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98884:9"/>
            <head>A Dialogue, &amp;c. Upon the HIGH-WAY.</head>
            <head type="sub">OCCASION'D By two Great Solemnities at <hi>New-caſtle</hi> upon <hi>Tine;</hi> The former <hi>February</hi> the 11th. 1684/5. At the Proclaiming of our Dread Soveraign King <hi>James</hi> the Second and Seventh: And the latter <hi>February</hi> the 13th. next after, at the bringing in of the New CHARTER.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tenant.</speaker>
               <p>SIR,</p>
               <l>I Was at <hi>New-Caſtle,</hi> where I trow ye ha' been,</l>
               <l>I ſaw
<note n="*" place="margin">ſuch.</note> ſyke a Sight there, as ne'er yet was ſeen;</l>
               <l>I thought they'd been Crowning a King or a Queen:</l>
               <l>Knights, Gallants, and Ladys, a hugious great Number,</l>
               <l>Bells rang, Minſtrills play'd, and Cannons did Thunder,</l>
               <l>But what was the meaning I canno' but wonder.</l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:98884:10"/>
               <l>Pikes, Muskets, and Drums, and
<note n="*" place="margin">many.</note> mony gay Fellows,</l>
               <l>The King's Health was Drunk at
<note n="‖" place="margin">ev'ry.</note> ilk' Tavern and Ale-houſe;</l>
               <l>Inſtead of fair Water their Fountains ſprang Clarret,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Good.</note> Geud Fellows came in, and amang 'm did ſhare it.</l>
               <l>They ranted the Day out, and when the Night came,</l>
               <l>I thought the
<note n="†" place="margin">whole.</note> hail Town had been
<note n="*" place="margin">Bonefires.</note> all in a Flame.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Land-lord,</hi> Hold, hold my Good-Neighbour, let me know what you ſay?</l>
               <l>I'll tell ye the meaning as well as I may;</l>
               <l>What—? Thund'ring of Cannons, there was no ſuch thing,</l>
               <l>'Twas the
<note n="‖" place="margin">
                     <hi>New-caſtle</hi> is the chief Town in thoſe parts.</note> Cock of the North was Clapping his Wing.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>But
<note n="*" place="margin">one.</note> ya thing I minded, reſolve me this caſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Two</note> Twa Paſſions appeared in
<note n="‖" place="margin">ev'ry</note> ilka Mans Face?</l>
               <l>The
<note n="*" place="margin">conſide.</note> ta ſide ſeem'd Merry, the t'other-ſide Mourn'd,</l>
               <l>And Sorrow to
<note n="†" place="margin">Gladneſs.</note> Blythneſs was inſtantly turn'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>Alaſs now ye pinch me! there is no denying,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Great Caeſar</hi> our Monarch was lying a dying,</l>
               <l>But when he exſpir'd and his Soul fled to Heav'n;</l>
               <l>Inſtead of himſelf his Second was giv'n.</l>
               <l>Now Sorrow! now Joy! nothing better cou'd do it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>But then
<note n="‖" place="margin">Charter.</note> twa days after, again they fell to it;</l>
               <l>Their
<note n="†" place="margin">Wofulneſs.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>waedeum ſeem'd vaniſh't; leſs ſign left of Grief;</l>
               <l>How came that about?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>I'll tell thee in brief.</l>
               <l>The day breaks agen, our Horizon is clear'd,</l>
               <l>The Sun in the South ſoon after appear'd:</l>
               <l>Obſerve when bright <hi>Phaebus</hi> at firſt takes his Riſe,</l>
               <l>He ſeems not ſo Glorious to faint mortal Eyes,</l>
               <l>Some Clouds may ſurround him, the Morning is chill,</l>
               <l>But upward advancing, Carreering it ſtill;</l>
               <l>The higher he mounts it, the warmer the day.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>I's
<note n="*" place="margin">I'm ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what Book-learn'd.</note> ſunckat beuk-learn'd, and I gueſs what you ſay.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>Then a full noon of Joy, poſſeſt ev'ry Heart,</l>
               <l>Old and Young, High and Low there Acted a part.</l>
               <l>Every Bigg-belly'd Wife eas'd her Apron-String,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>May this prove a Souldier to ſight for our King:</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:98884:10"/>
               <l>Ev'ry Girl of Fourteen wiſht her ſelf a Bride,</l>
               <l>For that,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>And another
<note n="‖" place="margin">good.</note> geud reaſon beſide.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">It was full Sea and a high Spring Tide, juſt when the King was Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed here.</note> Seas roar, Rivers ſwell, expreſſing their Joy,</l>
               <l>Th' harmonious Spheres ſound <hi>Vive le Roy.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>What was't they fetcht in with ſike Pomp and Pride?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>Their <hi>Charter,</hi> their <hi>Rule,</hi> their <hi>Light,</hi> and their <hi>Guide.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>They're mighty proundon't.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>So well may they, ſince,</l>
               <l>It's great Honour to merit that Grace from their Prince.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>Had I but kenn'd
<note n="†" place="margin">all.</note> aw, when I was in the Town,</l>
               <l>I'ad ſpent t'other Groat on the brisk-berry-brown;</l>
               <l>And when I've tell'd this to my
<note n="‖" place="margin">poor.</note> peur Wife
<note n="*" place="margin">old.</note> awld <hi>Megg,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>She'll noddle her Head tho' ſhe
<note n="‖" place="margin">cannot.</note> canno' lift Leg.</l>
               <l>But well away <hi>Landlord!</hi> the days we ha'ſeen,</l>
               <l>Had it
<note n="*" place="margin">always gone ſo.</note> aylways gane ſae, we happy had been!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>When Rebel-Phanaticks like Lions did roar,</l>
               <l>They mauld brave <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> and many <hi>Towns</hi> more,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>And
<note n="‖" place="margin">all.</note> aw that was Loyal they to the Ground bore.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>Like ſtupid dull Geeſe, they ſat rotten Eggs,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>And ſettling Religion, they jumbl'd it to Dregs.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>They cry'd up Religion, like Tygers they fought for't,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>But ne'er
<note n="*" place="margin">found.</note> faund it out 'till our Coffers were ſought for't.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>Tubs were made Pulpits.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>And Kirks turn'd to Stables.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>Cant paſs'd for Goſpel.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>Religion for Fables.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>They vaunted <hi>both</hi> Babel, <hi>and</hi> Dagon <hi>ſhou'd fall.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>But the Rubbiſh ſmoor'd King, Laws, Biſhops and all.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>Sacriledge, Treaſon, Blood, Plunder, and Rape.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>In truth it was well if our Wives did eſcape.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>Pretending our Freedom, they noos'd us in ſlav'ry.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>Made
<note n="‖" place="margin">holy.</note> haly pretences a Cloak for their Knav'ry.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>Our nak'd Breaſts expoſed to Bullets and Steel.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>By the Faith o' my Body I kenn that
<note n="*" place="margin">full-well.</note> fow-weel.</l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:98884:11"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>Eſtates were ſequeſt'red, and not a Groat left us.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>Of our
<note n="†" place="margin">Goods,</note> and our Gear, and geud-names they bereft us.</l>
               <l>When I
<note n="‖" place="margin">call to mind</note> unbethink me of
<note n="*" place="margin">thoſe</note> thea frights and fears</l>
               <l>This
<note n="‖" place="margin">poor old gray Beard hangs.</note> peur auld Gray-beard hings dreeping wi' Tears.</l>
               <l>I've gane to the Market, I've bought Beef and Mutton,</l>
               <l>I've ſaid to my Wife—<hi>Dame hing us the Pot on,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Here's Wheat-meal and Sewet, we'll have a Poak-Puddin,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Put a
<note n="‖" place="margin">handful</note> neef fow of Prunes in't, and make it a geud ane;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Theſe</note> 
                  <hi>Thea Traitors have come, (I ſpeak nathing but truth)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And not left me
<note n="‖" place="margin">one</note> ya bite on't to put in my Mouth.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I've tew'd this peur Carcaſs,
<note n="*" place="margin">both</note> baith weary and lame,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And
<note n="‖" place="margin">Then gone to Bed with an empty Belly.</note> ſyne gane to Bed with a tewm hungry wame.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I cannot but
<note n="*" place="margin">weep</note> greet Sir, this ſad tale to tell,</l>
               <l>But
<note n="‖" place="margin">more</note> mair for my Wife, and my Bairns, nor my
<note n="*" place="margin">ſelf;</note> ſel';</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="‖" place="margin">Who have looked car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly.</note> Wha've glowr'd in my Face, and cry'd <hi>what
<note n="*" place="margin">muſt</note> mun we eat?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When my Tears was their drink, and my Groans was their meat.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>But when God of his Mercy reſtor'd us our Prince,</l>
               <l>What plenty of good things have we had e'er ſince!</l>
               <l>What Subject of his had cauſe to complain?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>And what the Lord ſent us was allways our
<note n="‖" place="margin">own</note> aine.</l>
               <l>May-chance now and then a Sax-penny Seſs,</l>
               <l>My Pot neither boyl'd, nor my Spit jogg'd the leſs;</l>
               <l>I paid you my Rent, I keep't up my Credit;</l>
               <l>I've lent my Friend five Mark, and
<note n="*" place="margin">more</note> mair when I had it;</l>
               <l>I pity'd the Trav'ller that came to my
<note n="‖" place="margin">Door,</note> Deur,</l>
               <l>I had
<note n="*" place="margin">allways</note> ayllways a Morſell, to give to the
<note n="‖" place="margin">Poor.</note> Peur.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>We all liv'd in Peace with Bleſſings ten Thouſand,</l>
               <l>But our Bleſſing was
<note n="*" place="margin">Plotting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſo good a Prince.</note> curſt, when we made the wrong uſe on't;</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>We were ſerv'd in our kind, for our
<note n="‖" place="margin">ſelves</note> ſel's was the cauſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Great Charles!</hi> moſt renown'd may thy Memory be, on't.</l>
               <l>Thou found'ſt us all Slaves, but thou'ſt left us all Free,</l>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:98884:11"/>
               <l>We know thou'rt immortal, thou canſt not be dead;</l>
               <l>Thou'ſt but finiſht thy days-work, and ſo gone to Bed.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>Whiſht Landlord.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>Speak Tears.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>There's nae mair to be ſaid.</l>
               <l>But Sir, I've oft heard our
<note n="*" place="margin">The Clergy of the Church of <hi>England</hi> were ever Loyal.</note> geud Miniſter ſay,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jack-Presbyter fain wou'd be at his
<note n="‖" place="margin">old</note> auld play.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is the fo'ke
<note n="*" place="margin">all run mad,</note> aw gane fond, to play
<note n="†" place="margin">ſuch</note> ſyke a trick on't?</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="‖" place="margin">if they knew but what we know.</note> Gin they wiſt but what we wote, I trow they'd grow ſick on't.</l>
               <l>How
<note n="*" place="margin">go</note> gang they about us! the like was nev'r ſeen!</l>
               <l>What—? cheat us twice fairly before our awn
<note n="‖" place="margin">Eyes?</note> Een?</l>
               <l>Can the
<note n="†" place="margin">fooliſh Clowns</note> ſilly daft Carles think we'll ſtill be Fools?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>When they fall a working they want not their Tools;</l>
               <l>By Clubs, and Cabals, and by open attempting,</l>
               <l>By ſpreading falſe News, and by Conventicle-Canting.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>To cover their Knav'ry, they'll play at <hi>Bo-peep,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>About the Buſh <hi>(Tony,)</hi> or at <hi>Hide and go ſeek;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Sometimes they'll play fairly, and whiles they'll play <hi>Booty,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But gi' me him that's faithful becauſe it's his Duty,</l>
               <l>He'll work his
<note n="‖" place="margin">work</note> wark fairly, without Knaviſh drift;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That Blade for my
<note n="*" place="margin">Money,</note> Siller, he's faſt in the heft.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When Death becomes <hi>Plaintiff,</hi> and Traitor <hi>Defendant,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then 'ſpye well about ye, and mark but the end on't,</l>
               <l>He may chance to drop off, as other Men do;</l>
               <l>But rather knit up like a Bird in a bought;</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="‖" place="margin">Let it go as it will,</note> Gang that as it likes, his Memory's curſt,</l>
               <l>And
<note n="*" place="margin">ſomewhat</note> ſunckat comes after, I trow that's the worſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>Let's viſit the Shrines of thrice Noble <hi>Montroſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Pious <hi>Laud,</hi> Brave Lord <hi>Capel,</hi> and many of thoſe,</l>
               <l>Smell their Loyal-duſt, and its fragrant Scent,</l>
               <l>Makes the Spice of <hi>Arabia</hi> inſipid and faint:</l>
               <l>Perhaps Men may ſay, Here — ſuch an one lyes,</l>
               <l>But if he was Loyal, they'll ne'er ſay <hi>he dyes?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>True, Rebels and Traytors will nev'r be forgotten,</l>
               <l>Tho their Mem'ry ſtinks worſe then their Fleſh whilſt a-rotting.</l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:98884:12"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>Shou'd I put my kind to diſcredit and ſhame,</l>
               <l>They'll caſt up to my Bairns, when I'm dead and
<note n="‖" place="margin">gone,</note> gane,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Your Grandſir was hangit for being a Traytor;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>God
<note n="*" place="margin">Blefs us and heep us from any ſuch</note> ſafe us, and ſain us fra ony ſike matter.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>The greateſt of Beauty's by God ever giv'n,</l>
               <l>Was Order on Earth, and Order in Heav'n:</l>
               <l>By Pride and Diſorder great <hi>Lucifer</hi> fell,</l>
               <l>Yet he cannot rule without Order in Hell.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Devils allow <hi>Beelzebub</hi> to be their Prince, but Whigs diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>own all Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours.</note> Then wha deny's Order is warſe nor his ſel'.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>If then without order no Kingdom can ſtand,</l>
               <l>That muſt be the beſt which the powerful hand</l>
               <l>Of God, in his Wiſdom, has for us appointed.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>They're
<note n="‖" place="margin">infortunate or bewitch't</note> unſoncy that
<note n="*" place="margin">meddles</note> mells with th' Almighty's An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>I've read ſeveral Hiſt'rys, ſacred and profane,</l>
               <l>I've rang'd foreign Countrys with labour and pain,</l>
               <l>And I allways obſerv'd the People more bleſt,</l>
               <l>And richer, and ſtronger, and far leſs oppreſt</l>
               <l>By the worſt of their Kings, than the beſt of Uſurpers.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>My
<note n="‖" place="margin">Malediction</note> Maliſon light upon Government truckers.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>This truth (I believe) is by all men confeſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>What geud-luck ha' we then gets allways the beſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>But now our way parts, and there's no Hoſt-houſe,</l>
               <l>To drink the King's Health in a Loyal Carouſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>Had we but a Gallon of humming-Corn-Drink,</l>
               <l>I need no' to tell ye, ye
<note n="‖" place="margin">know</note> knaw what I think;</l>
               <l>Intruth my dear Land-lord, I'ſe vext to the
<note n="*" place="margin">Blood</note> Bleud.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>We'll ſing his good Health then.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>And that's e'en as geud.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <opener>To the Tune of Hey Boys up go we.</opener>
                  <lg>
                     <head>I.</head>
                     <l>Now who dare ſay <hi>brave Charles</hi> is gone,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Brave Charles</hi> is ſtill the ſame;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Brave Charles</hi> ſits ſafe on <hi>Charles</hi>'s Throne,</l>
                     <l>And only chang'd his Name.</l>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:98884:12"/>
                     <l>We <hi>Engliſh</hi>-men, how happy then,</l>
                     <l>Look here for Monarchy;</l>
                     <l>Our King nev'r dyes, nor from us flyes,</l>
                     <l>And hey-boys up ſtand we.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>II.</head>
                     <l>Hold off—touch not our <hi>Angel-Queen,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Flat Muſe fly not ſo high,</l>
                     <l>The Quinteſſence of all the Fruits,</l>
                     <l>Of fertile <hi>Italy.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Compariſon's not worth a Doit,</l>
                     <l>Here's matchleſs Majeſty,</l>
                     <l>Both he and ſhe in <hi>Honi Soit,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
                     <l>Still higher up go we.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>III.</head>
                     <l>Repent and turn miſ-guided Whigs,</l>
                     <l>Your Projects will not do;</l>
                     <l>Both Heav'n and Earth maintains the fight,</l>
                     <l>Againſt your Cauſe, and you:</l>
                     <l>We'll not refuſe your Friendſhip ſtill,</l>
                     <l>If you your faults will ſee;</l>
                     <l>Join hand in hand, let <hi>James</hi> command,</l>
                     <l>And none ſo high as we.</l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>Weell ſung honeſt Land-lord, but yet let me tell,</l>
               <l>It's pity nane ſhou'd have
<note n="‖" place="margin">ſuch</note> ſike ſport but your ſel'.</l>
               <l>Will ye let me ſing mine as well as I can?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>Ye're wellcome, begin, ye're a good Loyal Man.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <l>And is great <hi>Charles</hi> our Sov'raign dead!</l>
                  <l>Now fates do what ye can!</l>
                  <l>The Chriſtal drops bedew the Cheeks</l>
                  <l>Of
<note n="‖" place="margin">every</note> ilka Loyal Man.</l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:98884:13"/>
                  <l>Stop
<note n="†" place="margin">Floods</note> Fleuds of Tears, and flow
<note n="‖" place="margin">no more,</note> na maire,</l>
                  <l>Submit to Heav'ns decree;</l>
                  <l>We have a Plaiſter for our
<note n="*" place="margin">ſore,</note> ſare,</l>
                  <l>And ſtill Boys ſound are we.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <l>When Royal <hi>James</hi> to <hi>Scotland</hi> came,</l>
                  <l>Geud Lard, how
<note n="‖" place="margin">glad</note> blyth were we!</l>
                  <l>We danc't, we drank his Health, and Sang,</l>
                  <l>With mirth and merry glee:</l>
                  <l>We flang our ſel's down at his Feet,</l>
                  <l>Our
<note n="‖" place="margin">Necks</note> Craigs laid to his Knee,</l>
                  <l>And ay the
<note n="†" place="margin">lower</note> Laigher that we
<note n="‖" place="margin">bow'd</note> jowk't,</l>
                  <l>The higher up went we.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <l>You mighty Potentates abroad,</l>
                  <l>For
<note n="‖" place="margin">all</note> aw your brave Adventures,</l>
                  <l>Ye are but 'Prentices at Trade,</l>
                  <l>And newly Sign'd Indentures;</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="‖" place="margin">Almoſt</note> Amaiſt by ſax-ſcore Royal Kings,</l>
                  <l>We'll prove his Pedigree;</l>
                  <l>I've crack't the
<note n="*" place="margin">World</note> Warld
<note n="‖" place="margin">from</note> fra end to end,</l>
                  <l>And
<note n="*" place="margin">none ſo</note> nane ſae high as we.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Shou'd ſome hing lugg'd Whig ſneak under
<note n="†" place="margin">thoſe</note> thea Dykes,</l>
                  <l>He'll ſay to his
<note n="‖" place="margin">ſelf</note> ſel'—<hi>you's twa Tory Tykes;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But I care not a Button how many can hear;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A Fig for aw Phyſick when a Man can piſs clear.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>We've ſung the King's Health, we'll pray't if ye will.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>That's ev'ry way better, and better on ſtill.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>Then long live <hi>Great James,</hi> the Mirrour of Princes,</l>
               <l>May his Reign ne'er be troubl'd with Whiggiſh Pretences,</l>
               <l>May Plots and Conſpiracys blaſt in the Bud,</l>
               <l>And may we be happy in knowing our Good:</l>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:98884:13"/>
               <l>May no foreign Land make theſe Nations a By-word.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>Amen I pray God. Now Geud-night to ye Landlord.</l>
               <l>Ha-a-aw Landlord hanck your
<note n="†" place="margin">Horſe</note> Naig a while,</l>
               <l>For I ha' ridden full lang twa mile,</l>
               <l>Out of my
<note n="†" place="margin">way</note> Gate, to overtake ye,</l>
               <l>(For while I'm quick I'll ne'er forſake ye)</l>
               <l>I've ſpurr'd my Beaſt 'till he's gore
<note n="(a)" place="margin">blood,</note> bleud,</l>
               <l>But I ha'
<note n="(b)" place="margin">one</note> yane at hame as geud.</l>
               <l>Now this is it,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">ſoon</note> ſeun as we parted</l>
               <l>Another whimſey ſtraight upſtarted,</l>
               <l>Geud faith my very Heart did burn,</l>
               <l>And
<note n="(d)" place="margin">long'd</note> lang'd to have the t'other turn,</l>
               <l>And crack a bit, o' this ſame Faſhion.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>In <hi>Durham</hi> on the Coronation.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>Sir keep your
<note n="(e)" place="margin">appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</note> tryſt, and ye'll e'en win me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>I will not fail, if life be in me.</l>
            </sp>
            <trailer>The end of the firſt Dialogue.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="dialogue">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:98884:14"/>
            <head>A SECOND Dialogue, &amp;c. At an Inn in <hi>Durham, April</hi> the 23. 1685.</head>
            <head type="sub">BEING The Coronation-day of their moſt Sacred Majeſties, King <hi>James</hi> the Second and Seventh, and his moſt Illuſtrious Queen <hi>Mary.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">OCCASION'D By a moſt ſplendid Solemnity, that Day there.</head>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enters the</hi> Landlord <hi>to the</hi> Tenant <hi>At Eight a Clock at Night.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tenant.</speaker>
               <l>YE're wellcome Sir, now ſit ye down,</l>
               <l>For I have ſought throughout this Town,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="‖" place="margin">Indeed</note> Forſeuth I've had a
<note n="†" place="margin">weariſome</note> tyreſome chace,</l>
               <l>And fain wou'd I ha' ſeen your Face;</l>
               <l>God's
<note n="*" place="margin">B'eſſing</note> Benniſon light on your Heart,</l>
               <l>We'll crack a bit
<note n="†" place="margin">before</note> afore we part.</l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:98884:14"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>I had ſome buſineſs to do,</l>
               <l>Which made me take the ſtart of you:</l>
               <l>Draw in your Chair, ſit down I ſay;</l>
               <l>And tell me how you've ſpent this day?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>Nay
<note n="(a)" place="margin">pardoume</note> hald a caſt, I trow ye jear'd,</l>
               <l>Think ye that I'll be ſae
<note n="(b)" place="margin">ill-bred?</note> miſlear'd?</l>
               <l>It is the order of our Land,</l>
               <l>When Laird ſits down, let Plew-men ſtand.</l>
               <l>If
<note n="(c)" place="margin">any</note> ony chance to ſee, he'll tell,</l>
               <l>Give Bumpkin inch he'll take an ell.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>And if it were the ſame of us,</l>
               <l>There wou'd not be ſo great abuſe.</l>
               <l>Some Landlords are ſuch needleſs Waſters,</l>
               <l>They make their Tenants oft their Maſters;</l>
               <l>When we're to do our Sov'raigns Pleaſure,</l>
               <l>We may expect their help at leaſure:</l>
               <l>Howev'r you ſhew your Breeding there,</l>
               <l>Yet notwithſtanding here's a Chair;</l>
               <l>When you obey you're free from ſtripe,</l>
               <l>Here—take my Box and ſill your Pipe.</l>
               <l>If any Gentlemen here come in,</l>
               <l>And we Diſcourſes ſhou'd begin,</l>
               <l>Stand up 'till ſome bid you ſit down,</l>
               <l>And none will call you <hi>ſawcy Clown.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>There was brave Sights, I make no doubt</l>
               <l>But ye were ſtirring ſtill about,</l>
               <l>What did ye hear? What was't ye ſaw?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>I'll ne'er be
<note n="(d)" place="margin">able</note> yable to tell it
<note n="(e)" place="margin">all,</note> aw,</l>
               <l>I lik't what ever I did ſee,</l>
               <l>Except a
<note n="(f)" place="margin">willful</note> willfow deformity.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>Willful! Surely that's not fitting.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>As ſure as we're at Table ſitting.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Scotch</hi> Cuſtome is (I pray'e obſerve)</l>
               <l>A Rule fra
<note n="(g)" place="margin">which</note> whilk we never ſwerve;</l>
               <l>If we ha' ſcant a Mark o'Gear,</l>
               <l>We give our Bairns ſtill
<note n="(h)" place="margin">ſomewhat</note> ſunckat
<note n="(i)" place="margin">learning</note> lear;</l>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:98884:15"/>
               <l>And I my
<note n="‖" place="margin">ſelf,</note> ſel'
<note n="†" place="margin">poor</note> peur as you, ſee,</l>
               <l>Had ſome of that beſtow'd on me.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ovidius</hi> in his <hi>Metamorphos,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Has laid this thing
<note n="‖" place="margin">ſo</note> ſae plain before us:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Os homini ſublime dedit.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(Ye wote he was
<note n="*" place="margin">no Fool</note> nae Feul that ſaid it)</l>
               <l>And next to that, <hi>Coelum tueri;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Now what needs aw this
<note n="‖" place="margin">Coll kep't.</note> feery fary?</l>
               <l>Shou'd I take pains to
<note n="*" place="margin">crook my ſelf.</note> creuk my ſel',</l>
               <l>As
<note n="‖" place="margin">if I long'd to look</note> gin I lang'd to leuk like hell?</l>
               <l>The
<note n="*" place="margin">well fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd</note> well faur'd Ladys ſtrangely ſtoops,</l>
               <l>And out behind they ſtick their Croops,</l>
               <l>(From whence they came I canno' ſay,</l>
               <l>But <hi>Durham</hi>-Ladies were not they:</l>
               <l>Ev'ry of them beſide her Marrow,</l>
               <l>Walks e'en as ſtraight as ev'r was Arrow.)</l>
               <l>I
<note n="‖" place="margin">catch't ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den hold</note> Cleek't
<note n="†" place="margin">one</note> yane of them by the Arm,</l>
               <l>"And
<note n="*" place="margin">inquir'd</note> ſpeer'd
<note n="‖" place="margin">if</note> gin back ſide were wi' bairn,</l>
               <l>"Here's
<note n="‖" place="margin">Dung-hill</note> Middin-midwife juſt at hand,</l>
               <l>"Deliver and you'l ſtraighter ſtand:</l>
               <l>She did nathing but laugh and flyre,</l>
               <l>And cock't her tail twa Inches higher.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>Defects of Nature may be mended;</l>
               <l>But uſe right ſhape when God do's ſend it.</l>
               <l>Well, how prov'd you upon the Road?</l>
               <l>What paſt before ye went abroad?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>Up I got this Morning early,</l>
               <l>I joggit on
<note n="*" place="margin">ſlowly</note> hewly and fairly;</l>
               <l>And
<note n="‖" place="margin">always</note> ayle I whiſtled as I came,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The King enjoys his awn again.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Came to this
<note n="†" place="margin">dore</note> deur, lap off, and then</l>
               <l>Enquir'd for
<note n="*" place="margin">ſuch</note> ſyke a Gentleman;</l>
               <l>My very Heart was at my Mouth,</l>
               <l>When they ſaid, <hi>he's not here in truth.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:98884:15"/>
               <l>I gave my Beaſt to the young Man,</l>
               <l>Wha fetch't us in this
<note n="‖" place="margin">Silver</note> Siller Cann:</l>
               <l>I end-ways to the Stable ran,</l>
               <l>I ſaw your
<note n="†" place="margin">Nag,</note> Naig, elſe I'm a Whelp,</l>
               <l>I took his
<note n="*" place="margin">Flank, or Buttock</note> Leungyie ſike a skelp,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cobby,</hi> quo'd I, <hi>if thou be
<note n="†" place="margin">there</note> thair,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I's ſure thy Maiſter is no' far;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And then I ſaid to the young Man,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Set up my
<note n="‖" place="margin">Mare</note> Mier
<note n="†" place="margin">ſoon</note> ſeun as ye can;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rub her well down and give her hay,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I will no' leave this Town to day:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And if I find thee free fra
<note n="*" place="margin">Sloth,</note> Sleuth,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I'll lay thee ſax-pence in thy
<note n="‖" place="margin">hand.</note> luſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Geud-Wife us'd me Courteouſlie,</l>
               <l>I
<note n="†" place="margin">bow'd</note> jowk't to her, ſhe
<note n="*" place="margin">kneel'd</note> baik't to me;</l>
               <l>She ſet a
<note n="‖" place="margin">ſtool.</note> ſteul, and laid a Cuſhion,</l>
               <l>I drew my Box, and
<note n="†" place="margin">took a ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ff,</note> teuk a Sneeſhon;</l>
               <l>She fetcht
<note n="*" place="margin">cold</note> cald Roſt-beef, Bread and Cheeſe;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Put to your hand, eat what yepleaſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If ye ha' Travel'd far to day,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ye may
<note n="‖" place="margin">fall</note> faw Hungry by the way.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>She
<note n="†" place="margin">ſpoke</note> ſpack like fo'ke o'th' <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation,</l>
               <l>But I
<note n="*" place="margin">muſt</note> mun tell't o'mine awn Faſhion.</l>
               <l>I
<note n="‖" place="margin">ask't</note> ſpeer'd what news in this geud Town?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quo' ſhe, this day King</hi> James <hi>takes Crown.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Such-like</note> 
                  <hi>Sik'lyke will e'en our Gracious Queen:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A bleſter Couple never was ſeen,</l>
               <l>God grant them
<note n="*" place="margin">long</note> lang in peace to Reign,</l>
               <l>The
<note n="‖" place="margin">longer</note> langer
<note n="†" place="margin">more is</note> mair's their Subjects gain:</l>
               <l>A Prince indeed was his dear Brother,</l>
               <l>The Lord has granted
<note n="*" place="margin">ſuch</note> ſike another;</l>
               <l>Were I a man, my very bleud,</l>
               <l>I'de freely ſpend, to do them goud;</l>
               <l>And we ha' chos'n at our Elections,</l>
               <l>Four Loyal Men without exceptions.</l>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:98884:16"/>
               <l>And all the
<note n="‖" place="margin">Country</note> Keuntry round about,</l>
               <l>Are come to make a Loyal ſhout;</l>
               <l>Stay but a while ye'll hear them do't.</l>
               <l>Geud deed, thought I, if I be heer,</l>
               <l>This
<note n="†" place="margin">jolly wife</note> Carlin is a Cavalier.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>What will the Whigs,</hi> ſaid I, <hi>think now?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For they
<note n="*" place="margin">muſt</note> mun either break or bow.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Whigs,</hi> quo' ſhe, <hi>are ſae run down,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Not
<note n="‖" place="margin">one</note> yane about, nor in this Town.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Said I, unleſs ye over-aw them,</l>
               <l>Truſt ſome as far as ye can throw them.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nae hough-bands now for Godly helping?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And has Sweet-lips gi'en o're his yelping?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Blind</hi> Homer<hi>'s Sences quite decay'd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The
<note n="†" place="margin">holy</note> haly Siſters all ov'r-lay'd?</l>
               <l>Quo ſhe again, my Friend I feel,</l>
               <l>Ye
<note n="*" place="margin">inquire the way ye know</note> ſpeer the Gate ye kenn right weel.</l>
               <l>Ye ſeem a <hi>Scotch-man</hi> by your Tongue,</l>
               <l>Ha' ye liv'd in this Keuntry long?</l>
               <l>I
<note n="‖" place="margin">love</note> leuve your <hi>Scotch-men</hi> in my Heart,</l>
               <l>'Cauſe with our King ye
<note n="†" place="margin">took</note> teuk a part.</l>
               <l>Dame, I to her, I can aſſure 'em,</l>
               <l>Ye did the ſame your
<note n="*" place="margin">ſelv's</note> ſel's at <hi>Deurham.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Send in a
<note n="†" place="margin">quart</note> Chappin of your Wine,</l>
               <l>I'll drink their Healths before I Dine.</l>
               <l>It was in
<note n="‖" place="margin">jeſt</note> mowes that I did
<note n="†" place="margin">inquire</note> ſpeer,</l>
               <l>But
<note n="*" place="margin">ſince</note> ſen ye are a Cavalier,</l>
               <l>I'll
<note n="‖" place="margin">whiſper</note> rowne ye
<note n="†" place="margin">ſomewhat</note> ſunck at in your ear.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I
<note n="*" place="margin">know</note> ken this County well eneugh,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="‖" place="margin">take no notice</note> 
                  <hi>Miskenn I tell'd ye.</hi> Then ſhe leugh.</l>
               <l>I knew this ere I hither came,</l>
               <l>Or elſe I had no' ſteer'd fra hame.</l>
               <l>I
<note n="†" place="margin">Command'd</note> garr'd a Barber come to me,</l>
               <l>He
<note n="*" place="margin">Trimm'd</note> Cow'd my Beard as you may ſee.</l>
               <l>I ſet my
<note n="‖" place="margin">ſelf</note> ſel' in ſeemly poſture,</l>
               <l>For Decency is beſt ye know Sir;</l>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:98884:16"/>
               <l>Eſpecially at this geud time,</l>
               <l>When
<note n="†" place="margin">every</note> ilka body will be fine.</l>
               <l>And
<note n="*" place="margin">then</note> ſyne I drew this
<note n="‖" place="margin">Crevat</note> Craigclaith out,</l>
               <l>She ty'd it faſt my Neck about;</l>
               <l>She ſigh't a little bit, and ſaid,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My Husband has been twelve Months dead.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And
<note n="†" place="margin">inquired</note> ſpeer'd, <hi>ha'ye a wife at hame.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I
<note n="*" place="margin">ſmiled,</note> ſmirk't, and then ſhe bluſh't for ſhame.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If ye be
<note n="‖" place="margin">going</note> ganging out o'
<note n="†" place="margin">dore,</note> deur,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Take my Advice, ſhe add<hi>'s, be ſure,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That your Purs-pocket be well button'd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>There will be Lowns, ye need no' doubt on't.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>When ye are
<note n="(d)" place="margin">looking, or wondring.</note> glowring at a Sign,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Or ſee them ſcamp'ring for the Wine:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or in the Croud a little to linger,</l>
               <l>Into your
<note n="(e)" place="margin">Pocket</note> Poutch he'l popp his Finger:</l>
               <l>And when ye have met with the loſs,</l>
               <l>Ye may
<note n="(f)" place="margin">go home</note> gang hame by weeping Croſs.</l>
               <l>They'l tice you in at Cards to play,</l>
               <l>And let you win a Deal or
<note n="(g)" place="margin">two;</note> twa;</l>
               <l>But if they find that ye will bend,</l>
               <l>Then harken to the hinder end:</l>
               <l>We ha' nae
<note n="(h)" place="margin">Whores</note> 'Hewrs, that's our geud luck,</l>
               <l>Therefore your Fleſh ye canno' truck,</l>
               <l>But if ye
<note n="(i)" place="margin">travel</note> gang to other places,</l>
               <l>And ye ſtand ſtaring in their Faces,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(k)" place="margin">one</note> Yane will draw up to you and ſay,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mine honeſt Country-man,
<note n="(l)" place="margin">good morrow, or good even,</note> geud day,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I fancy ye're ſome Friend o' mine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Will ye take a
<note n="(m)" place="margin">Pint</note> Mutch-kin o' Wine?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet have a care of her, ſhe's nought,</l>
               <l>Tho your Gray-hairs may have Green thought.</l>
               <l>Dame, I reply'd, how can ye tell?</l>
               <l>I trow ye Judge me by your ſel?</l>
               <l>Tho I ſaid ſae, ſhe did no' ſtown,</l>
               <l>But
<note n="(n)" place="margin">laugh'r,</note> leugh, and call'd me
<note n="(o)" place="margin">Waggiſh Body.</note> 
                  <hi>Limmen-lown.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:98884:17"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Put on your
<note n="(p)" place="margin">Gloves,</note> Gleuves, here take your Staff,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Twill keep a ruffling Fellow off,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gi me your Cloak and
<note n="(q)" place="margin">Cloak-bag</note> Knap-ſack too,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I'll lay them ſafely up for you.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If it were full o' burning Gold,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>It ſhan't be hurt were it untold.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If ye have ought to buy or ſell,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Adviſe with me, God ſpeed you well.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Maiſtriſs, quo'd I, ye are kind-hearted,</l>
               <l>I thank ye for't; and ſae we parted.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>As I was walking in the Street,</l>
               <l>Some old acquaintances I meet,</l>
               <l>All brave and Loyal Gentlemen,</l>
               <l>Who ſtoutly backt King <hi>Charles,</hi> ev'n when</l>
               <l>His Rebel-Subjects War declar'd,</l>
               <l>My ſelf with them a Fortune ſhar'd,</l>
               <l>At the <hi>Black-Horſe</hi> a while did tarry,</l>
               <l>And drunk ſome Healths to <hi>James</hi> and <hi>Mary.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>At afternoon to th' Croſs we came,</l>
               <l>Where twice or thrice we did the ſame;</l>
               <l>But after that appear'd no more,</l>
               <l>For I'm grown old, my Bones are ſore,</l>
               <l>With riding hither, tho my heart,</l>
               <l>As ſound as ev'r in ev'ry part.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>An' pleaſe your Worſhip, I'll declare</l>
               <l>What I ſaw publick e'ry where.</l>
               <l>Nev'r
<note n="(r)" place="margin">look</note> leuk for half there was
<note n="(ſ)" place="margin">ſo</note> ſae much,</l>
               <l>But here and there I'll give a touch.</l>
               <l>The Sherif ſent the Gentry warning,</l>
               <l>To meet him heer by time this Morning:</l>
               <l>Accordingly the ſame they did.</l>
               <l>And muſter'd on the <hi>Bella's-head,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Down <hi>Elvat</hi> to the Market place,</l>
               <l>With cheerfulneſs in
<note n="(t)" place="margin">every</note> ilka Face.</l>
               <l>At ſev'ral Taverns drunk a health,</l>
               <l>There was nae grudging of their Wealth;</l>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:98884:17"/>
               <l>Nor did they ſtick to be at Charge,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Tory-Ribbons</hi> rich and large,</l>
               <l>Whoſe various Colours glitt'ring ſhone,</l>
               <l>Like Roſes in the Morning <hi>Sun.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Loyal Tradeſmen preſent were,</l>
               <l>To wait on Aldermen, and Mayor,</l>
               <l>With Banners flying in the Air.</l>
               <l>Trumpets and Drums, ay Bag-Pipes too,</l>
               <l>With what ev'r elſe cou'd help their Shew.</l>
               <l>Reports did Eccho from their Tongues</l>
               <l>Supplying want of muckle Guns,</l>
               <l>Fra Morn till Night the Bells ding-dongs.</l>
               <l>The Mayor invites them to th'
<note n="†" place="margin">Tol-Booth</note> Tow-beuth,</l>
               <l>Drunk-Healths huzzaing ſtill, forſeuth,</l>
               <l>It cou'd not
<note n="*" place="margin">hold</note> hald the ha'fe in truth:</l>
               <l>The
<note n="(a)" place="margin">reſt</note> laive ſtood waiting for the name</l>
               <l>Of ev'ry Health—Huzza—the ſame.</l>
               <l>And next was made a wellcome Motion,</l>
               <l>Up to the Abbey in Devotion:</l>
               <l>(For let Men frolick what they will,</l>
               <l>The Fear of God's the beſt thing ſtill.)</l>
               <l>The like in <hi>Deurham</hi> ne'er was ſeen,</l>
               <l>As they went o'er the Palace-green;</l>
               <l>The Officers of the Train-Bands,</l>
               <l>In Coats of richeſt Scarlet ſtands,</l>
               <l>'Till ev'ry one in his degree,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">Took</note> Teuk place and ſae walkt orderly.</l>
               <l>Now having begg'd th' Almighty's Grace,</l>
               <l>Back they return to th' Market-place,</l>
               <l>In Splendour, and with ſtately Pace.</l>
               <l>At twelve a Clock they went to dine,</l>
               <l>With plenty of brave Cheer and Wine.</l>
               <l>Tho Wine may keep the Puddins warm,</l>
               <l>A little Meat Sir, do's nae harm:</l>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:98884:18"/>
               <l>It's dangerous for to carouſe</l>
               <l>With empty Tripes the hail day thus,</l>
               <l>(Mortar and Stanes make
<note n="‖" place="margin">ſtrongeſt</note> ſtranggeſt houſe.)</l>
               <l>The Trumpeters rich Livery'd towrs,</l>
               <l>And there ſpent they ſome twa'r three hours.</l>
               <l>Having tane featly of their fare,</l>
               <l>To Kirk and heard the Ev'ning prayer.</l>
               <l>That ended here began the game,</l>
               <l>The Mayors muckle Bane-fire ſet on Flame.</l>
               <l>Alas! alas! th' Aſſociation!</l>
               <l>The Godly's Darling of the Nation,</l>
               <l>The Maſter-piece of <hi>Tony</hi>'s Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks contriv'd for purpoſe holy;</l>
               <l>And eke the
<note n="*" place="margin">pretty</note> deft Excluſion-Bill,</l>
               <l>The Royal Lines Purgation-Pill;</l>
               <l>The grounds of Houſe of Common's ſtill,</l>
               <l>Condens't, prepar'd by Art and Skill:</l>
               <l>In Fire-ſhip Sails, tells <hi>Tony</hi> news.</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Deurham</hi>'s churliſh vile abuſe!</l>
               <l>The Black box fly's with flaming wings.</l>
               <l>Cramm'd with a race of Cully-Kings!</l>
               <l>Then to the
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mouth of the Fountain, which ſerves the Town</note> Pant, open'd the ſpout,</l>
               <l>Hey-daſh, the Claret-wine ſprang out,</l>
               <l>It hiſs't, and fizz'd, and flow'd amain,</l>
               <l>As if <hi>Bacchus</hi> had breath'd a vein.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">None</note> Nane offer'd Rudeneſs there, untill</l>
               <l>The Gentry firſt had got their will,</l>
               <l>Which was the ſame repeated ſtill.</l>
               <l>That
<note n="(c)" place="margin">done</note> deun on Shoulders they did climb,</l>
               <l>With he o'er her, and ſhe o'er him;</l>
               <l>The Squibs and Crackers ev'ry where:</l>
               <l>A Wag was there gave me my ſhare;</l>
               <l>For he
<note n="(d)" place="margin">threw one</note> flang yane upon my
<note n="(e)" place="margin">britches,</note> breeks,</l>
               <l>(E'en ſhame enough be in his Cheeks)</l>
               <l>And truly Sir it burnt my Leg,</l>
               <l>And garr'd me feek like Hen with Egg.</l>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:98884:18"/>
               <l>The Mayor invites this gen'rous train,</l>
               <l>All into the Tow-beuth again;</l>
               <l>I need no' tell their deed, it's plain:</l>
               <l>They out at Windows Sweet-meats throw,</l>
               <l>Cov'ring the Streets like flaggs of Snow;</l>
               <l>'Till by the Ears the Gatherers go.</l>
               <l>They bid Drums beat, and Trumpets ſound,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For we will take the tother round:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Some led, others follow'd the ſcent,</l>
               <l>Up to the Caſtle Gates they went.</l>
               <l>Hamper of Wine, with rich ſtrong Beer,</l>
               <l>Was drunk about the
<note n="(f)" place="margin">Bonefire.</note> Bane-fire there;</l>
               <l>Nor fuell, nor ſtrangg drink was ſpar'd,</l>
               <l>For <hi>come wha will</hi> i'th' Colledge yard.</l>
               <l>To Crown this great Solemnity,</l>
               <l>Again they to the Tavern hye;</l>
               <l>The tother Health and ſae geud-night,</l>
               <l>And that ſet ſome of them juſt right:</l>
               <l>But pray you Sir, miſtake not me,</l>
               <l>For there was nae <hi>indecencie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But men in ſyke a caſe as this,</l>
               <l>Will ſtrein a buckle.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>No great miſs.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>The Towns-mens Bane-fires towards the Even,</l>
               <l>Burnt fra five hours, 'till lang paſt ſeaven;</l>
               <l>And Healths they drunk
<note n="(g)" place="margin">very hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily.</note> juſt helter-skelter,</l>
               <l>But nev'r a
<note n="(h)" place="margin">Soul</note> Saul in mire did welter.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>Here ev'ry thing was order'd ſit,</l>
               <l>They like brave <hi>Hero</hi>'s carry'd it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>Ha' ye a mind to take your reſt?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>Nay not this hour; I think ye'ad beſt</l>
               <l>Begin ſome Song, or pleaſant Story.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>And I have baith Sir, ready for ye.</l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:98884:19"/>
            <p> 
               <gap reason="music">
                  <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
               </gap> THis <hi>Jennet</hi> is a Bonny Laſs, This <hi>Jennet</hi> is my Deary, What then need I ligg by my ſel', And <hi>Jennets</hi> bed ſae near me? ╌</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>How—? hold your peace, what's this you ſay?</l>
               <l>Sing me a Song fit for the Day.</l>
               <l>Had you ſeen what I ſaw of late,</l>
               <l>Ye wou'd not ſing at that wild rate.</l>
               <l>What—? can there be no Merriment,</l>
               <l>But what proceeds from baſe Intent?</l>
               <l>Is't not a ſhame that Chriſtian Breath,</l>
               <l>Shou'd to a ſcandal turn their Faith?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>This Wine's
<note n="(i)" place="margin">almoſt</note> amaiſt got in my Head,</l>
               <l>I make mair haſt nor meet geud-ſpeed;</l>
               <l>My Tongue is grown ſae ſlip and ſlidder,</l>
               <l>It glents and glyd's I knaw not whither;</l>
               <l>It's no' the
<note n="(k)" place="margin">Song</note> Sang that I intended,</l>
               <l>But pardon this, and I will mend it.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(l)" place="margin">give</note> Gi'me but leave to wet my Whiſtle,</l>
               <l>And i'll ſing you the Royal Thiſtle.</l>
            </sp>
            <lg>
               <gap reason="music">
                  <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <l>THe Thiſtle is the Healing Plant,</l>
               <l>What then need I to fear me,</l>
               <l>For my geud Health I nev'r can want,</l>
               <l>The Thiſtle grows ſo near me:</l>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:98884:19"/>
               <l>It cures Convulſions (in the State)</l>
               <l>It helps aw theſe are aguiſh,</l>
               <l>And Raging Feavers it will 'bate,</l>
               <l>Al—be—it they were Plaguiſh.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>Wha canno' leave the Thiſtle weel,</l>
               <l>Are oddly gi'en to Folly,</l>
               <l>Take thou of it and thou'll ne'er feel,</l>
               <l>Diſeaſe of Melancholy:</l>
               <l>Againſt the Rickets it is geud,</l>
               <l>The Ligaments it looſes,</l>
               <l>And purify's corrupted Bleud;</l>
               <l>Sae never ſpare thy doſes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>III.</head>
               <l>It helps the Hearing and the Sight,</l>
               <l>Green Wounds, and the Vertigo,</l>
               <l>'Twill keep thy
<note n="*" place="margin">blooming</note> bleuming Beauty bright,</l>
               <l>If thou'lt but do as we do,</l>
               <l>Againſt the Bitings of mad Dogs,</l>
               <l>Strong Poyſon, Worms and Vermin:</l>
               <l>What then are they but ſilly Rogues,</l>
               <l>That leuves no' what's nae harm in!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>IV.</head>
               <l>The Thiſtle branches out it's Leaves,</l>
               <l>And nev'r keeps them togither,</l>
               <l>To all it's Friends it ſhelter gives,</l>
               <l>In time of Stormy Weather:</l>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:98884:20"/>
               <l>But Rebel if thou dar'ſt be ſeen,</l>
               <l>(I hope we need no fear thee)</l>
               <l>The prickl's will
<note n="‖" place="margin">prick out thine eyes.</note> jagg out thine een,</l>
               <l>The Thiſtle will ſit near thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>That's ſomewhat like, but yet my Friend,</l>
               <l>I hope ye have not made an end,</l>
               <l>What is your Story?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>'Pon my
<note n="*" place="margin">oath,</note> yaith,</l>
               <l>It's Piper
<note n="‖" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tapski</hi>'s</note> 
                  <hi>Tony</hi>'s Life and Death.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>Then let me hear't from end to end?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>With brev'ty Sir, I do intend.</l>
               <l>Firſt place I will deſcribe his Perſon,</l>
               <l>(It was an ugly ill ſhap't Whoreſon!)</l>
               <l>His Looks, his Gate, and all was odious,</l>
               <l>As
<note n="*" place="margin">many</note> mony ſhapes as e'er had <hi>Proteus;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A reſtiff, Croſs-grain'd teethy Ape,</l>
               <l>A Devil ſure in Monkeys ſhape.</l>
               <l>Yet knew right well this wylie Elf,</l>
               <l>That nane cou'd play like to his ſelf.</l>
               <l>When
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Weddings</note> Brydals, or Horſe-Races fell,</l>
               <l>Still piper <hi>Tony</hi> bears the Bell:</l>
               <l>Of aw the pipers I did ſee,</l>
               <l>This piper <hi>Tony</hi> wan the
<note n="(b)" place="margin">degree.</note> gree.</l>
               <l>And yet by miſſing of his
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Tune,</note> Spring,</l>
               <l>He had
<note n="(d)" place="margin">almoſt</note> amaiſt
<note n="(e)" place="margin">undone</note> undeun the King;</l>
               <l>For right or
<note n="(f)" place="margin">wrong</note> wrang he made
<note n="(g)" place="margin">he made no matter,</note> nae matter,</l>
               <l>So he cou'd fiſh in
<note n="(h)" place="margin">troubl'd water.</note> Drumly-water.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>I prethee man how can that be?</l>
               <l>It's wonderful and ſtrange to me,</l>
               <l>That he by miſſing of a Spring,</l>
               <l>Cou'd e'er have hurt ſo great a King!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>Sir it is true, for I ſuppoſe,</l>
               <l>He plays nae Tune where e'er he goes,</l>
               <l>But <hi>Oliver lend me thy Noſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:98884:20"/>
               <l>Or ſometimes having tane a freſh-cup,</l>
               <l>He'll rumble you out, <hi>down drops the Biſhop.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Had he hit right it wou'd ha' been,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The King enjoys his awn agen,</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>I muſt confeſs that was a bad-one,</l>
               <l>But tell me what his Pipes were made on?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Imprimis</hi> (for I'll gang by order)</l>
               <l>The <hi>Chanter was an awld Recorder.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>It's firſt Maiſter came fra the
<note n="(i)" place="margin">Weſt-Cheſter</note> Weſt,</l>
               <l>Some thinks he play'd on it the beſt</l>
               <l>Of
<note n="(k)" place="margin">any</note> ony he on <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ground;</l>
               <l>They ſay his Marrow cann't be found;</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(l)" place="margin">who knows</note> Wha kenns a Pipe will ſur'ly grant Sir,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(m)" place="margin">Moſt</note> Maiſt of the skill lies in the <hi>Chanter:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His was of <hi>Willy Lenthals</hi> faſhion,</l>
               <l>Bor'd by the Wiſdom of the Nation,</l>
               <l>They try'd and try'd it o're again,</l>
               <l>And ſtill they
<note n="(n)" place="margin">found</note> fand that it
<note n="(o)" place="margin">ſpoke</note> ſpack plain;</l>
               <l>But yet it was an
<note n="(p)" place="margin">unknow'n</note> uncouth thing,</l>
               <l>It play'd for
<note n="(q)" place="margin">any</note> ony but the King;</l>
               <l>Tho' trott to <hi>Tyburn</hi> e'en wha will,</l>
               <l>It skreems a Huntſup with great skill.</l>
               <l>Yet when the Doctor's caſe came on,</l>
               <l>It did but wheezle in its tone.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(r)" place="margin">He was a Rebel-preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Reformer in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> who, having inflam'd his Country, and deſtroyed his Prince, his laſt Sickneſs (the Plague) took him; and to terrifie his Country, and encourage his Followers, he inloin'd them to flea off his Skin, and make a Drum of it. He was call'd the <hi>Monachomaxtix,</hi> from the great pleaſure he took in killing Monks for his ſport.</note> 
                  <hi>Ziſca</hi> the famous <hi>Monachomaxtix,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Wha in <hi>Bohemia</hi> play'd his Dog tricks,</l>
               <l>When he march't off he gari'd his pelt,</l>
               <l>Be made a Drum, dead heard, quick felt,</l>
               <l>Our Pipes b'ing near to that ſame faſhion,</l>
               <l>For playing thorow-Reformation,</l>
               <l>The Baggs were of that very Leather,</l>
               <l>Whilk keep't <hi>Nol</hi>'s
<note n="(ſ)" place="margin">ſcalp</note> pow fra Wind and Weather.</l>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:98884:21"/>
               <l>And lac't about, wi' skimmering-tinſel,</l>
               <l>Wov'n by a Whiggiſh Common Council.</l>
               <l>The Bellows were <hi>Bucchanan's</hi> Lungs,</l>
               <l>The flaps were <hi>Baxter's, Welſh's</hi> Tongues.</l>
               <l>The Reeds, Diſſenters Throats and Weaſands;</l>
               <l>The Drones, the ſhanks of
<note n="(t)" place="margin">Country Peaſants:</note> Keuntry Peaſants:</l>
               <l>The Blaſt was <hi>Rombals</hi> beſt Swan quill,</l>
               <l>Flap't with an
<note n="(u)" place="margin">old</note> ald <hi>Excluſion-Bill.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Wind-fald, and the Bellow's-Stockead,</l>
               <l>Were pieces of a brok'-<hi>Black-Box-lid.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Joints were turn'd to their degrees,</l>
               <l>In <hi>Calvin</hi>'s Reformation Trees.</l>
               <l>A bunch was hung where
<note n="(x)" place="margin">The Piper at a Wedding has always a piece of the Brides Garter ty'd about his pipes.</note> Ribbon glances,</l>
               <l>Of printed Votes, and Ordinances,</l>
               <l>Ty'd on with—<hi>Thanks to theſe who ſends us.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Now <hi>Saundy</hi> cry's to <hi>Kirſhin—Hony!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>What
<note n="(y)" place="margin">very pretty</note> winſome Pipes has little</hi> Tony!</l>
               <l>My Dow, quo-ſhe, they're wond'rous bonny!</l>
               <l>What Heav'nly Muſick will be made!</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tony</hi> hears that and nods his Head:</l>
               <l>Now we may dance o'er dyke and hedge,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But well-a-neer, at</hi> Bothwell Bridge,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They jobb'd a ſharp whittle in behind,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And after that his Baggs skaild Wind.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>An unexſpected by blow, which,</l>
               <l>Garr'd <hi>Tony</hi> ſcratch where't did not itch.</l>
               <l>He ſtitch't them cloſely up again,</l>
               <l>And on to <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> they came,</l>
               <l>There skreem'd, and raird beyond all ayme.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>Why did they to that place reſort?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>The <hi>Landlord</hi> was to hold a Court,</l>
               <l>And there his <hi>Tenants</hi> were attending,</l>
               <l>Sundry debates, preuving and fending:</l>
               <l>And when their buſineſs is
<note n="(z)" place="margin">done,</note> deun,</l>
               <l>They always gang to get a
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Spoonful</note> Speun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98884:21"/> of ſtout humming nappy Ale,</l>
               <l>And then the Piper will no' fail</l>
               <l>To <hi>Jenk</hi> a Huntſup o're the plain;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Till aw their jibblets jet again.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But yet, Sir, ye
<note n="(b)" place="margin">muſt</note> mun underſtand</l>
               <l>Another Card in <hi>Tony</hi>'s hand.</l>
               <l>A noble Lady there did live,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">Named</note> Yeleap't <hi>Madam Prerogotive:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Sprung from a Royal ſtock was ſhe,</l>
               <l>A Miracle of Courteſie;</l>
               <l>And for her Equipage and Honour,</l>
               <l>Some dainty Damſels waited on her.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(d)" place="margin">Among</note> Amang the
<note n="(e)" place="margin">reſt</note> laive was Propertie,</l>
               <l>A ſtrapping Wench as
<note n="(f)" place="margin">one</note> yane ſhall ſee;</l>
               <l>She came of honeſt Parentage,</l>
               <l>And got to an indiff'rent age:</l>
               <l>She was Houſe-keeper to my
<note n="(g)" place="margin">My Lady Prerogative.</note> Lady,</l>
               <l>And to ſpeak truth was always ready,</l>
               <l>To get fo'ke what they wou'd be at;</l>
               <l>And bairns their Meat, and
<note n="(h)" place="margin">ſuch</note> ſyke as that.</l>
               <l>She was high in my Lady's Favour,</l>
               <l>And large Allowances ſhe gave her.</l>
               <l>What ever was my Lady's fare,</l>
               <l>Still Property
<note n="(i)" place="margin">muſt</note> mann have her ſhare;</l>
               <l>And if her head had tane an aiking,</l>
               <l>My Lady's heart wou'd fall a quaking.</l>
               <l>Had ye but ſeen't ye wou'd ha' ſworn,</l>
               <l>She had her of her Body born:</l>
               <l>There's nathing there cou'd run a-reel,</l>
               <l>If Maiſtriſs Property were weel.</l>
               <l>'Till in Concluſion it befell,</l>
               <l>That Property
<note n="(k)" place="margin">forgot</note> misken'd her
<note n="(l)" place="margin">ſelf</note> ſel';</l>
               <l>And needs wou'd be the better Woman.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>Indeed my friend that's very common;</l>
               <l>When Servants long time with us live,</l>
               <l>They think they merit all we give.</l>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:98884:22"/>
               <l>It's true, ſome uſe old Servants worſe</l>
               <l>Than uſeleſs Dog, or out-worn Horſe.</l>
               <l>Again, when Servants learn to know</l>
               <l>Their Buſineſs, then they ſawey grow;</l>
               <l>In either party ought to be</l>
               <l>Diſcretion and Civility.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>At this my Lady was ſurpriz'd,</l>
               <l>And Property ſhe thus advis'd.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My dow</hi> (quo ſhe) <hi>It's very ſtrange,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That I ſhould find in you this change!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My Buſineſs is quite neglected,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And
<note n="(a)" place="margin">nothing done</note> nathing deun as I directed;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>There is ſome Maggot in your pate,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That alters you ſae
<note n="(b)" place="margin">much</note> meikle of late,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If ye intend to pick a Quarrel</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With me, be wiſe, or at your Peril;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fall to your Duty as before,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>You'll ſee I'll give the matter o'er;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And ye ſhall nev'r crave twice of me</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The ſmalleſt Penny of your
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Wages.</note> Fee.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But Property was in the huff,</l>
               <l>And oft ſhe wou'd go in a ſnuff:</l>
               <l>She grew at laſt that nane cou'd guide her,</l>
               <l>My Lady then was forc't to chidd her.</l>
               <l>Into a private Room they draw,</l>
               <l>And thus to her ſhe laid the Law.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Have I brought thee up
<note n="(d)" place="margin">peremptory</note> paughty Quean,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Like Bird to pick out mine awn
<note n="(e)" place="margin">Eyes?</note> Een?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Had'ſt thou in thee the leaſt
<note n="(f)" place="margin">Common-Senſe.</note> Rumgumption,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thou'd ſcorn aw ſik'lyke Preſumption.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>By the
<note n="(g)" place="margin">whole World</note> hail Waurld it will be thought,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thou has been better fed nor taught.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Think'ſt thou I'm in neceſſity,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To turn thy
<note n="(h)" place="margin">bold impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Jade.</note> tauntrils-tail on me?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If ſae it be, then look about ye,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And try gin I cann't live without ye.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:98884:22"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>I trow ye'll be the firſt will rue,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>(I's Cox't if my Words preuve no' true:)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Experience will this unriddle;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sae take a Spring of thine awn Fiddle.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How fain wou'd ſhe had her reclaim'd,</l>
               <l>But all Expedients were disdain'd:</l>
               <l>For aw ſhe cou'd do for her Life,</l>
               <l>Was but againſt the ſtream to ſtrive.</l>
               <l>Tho Property had got this ſcooling,</l>
               <l>She ſcorn'd a jot to leave her fooling,</l>
               <l>But turn'd her foot, disdain'd to bow;</l>
               <l>And in Deriſion wry'd her
<note n="(i)" place="margin">Mouth.</note> Mow:</l>
               <l>When wanton
<note n="(k)" place="margin">Horſe or Mare.</note> Yaud has caſt her Rider,</l>
               <l>And tane ſike freeks that
<note n="(l)" place="margin">none</note> nane can guide her,</l>
               <l>Under her Feet ſhe gets her
<note n="(m)" place="margin">Bridle or Halter.</note> Branks,</l>
               <l>And ſtark-horn-mad ſhe ply's her Shanks:</l>
               <l>Now down before, now up behind,</l>
               <l>Now Noſe, now Tail fly's in the Wind:</l>
               <l>She Sneers and Whinny's — <hi>Whilly-Lilly,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(Fo'ke think's the De'il's poſſeſt o'th' Filly.)</l>
               <l>At this ſame rate far'd Property,</l>
               <l>As
<note n="(n)" place="margin">ſoon</note> ſeun as ſhe had tane the
<note n="(o)" place="margin">any manner of ill Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</note> gee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>By what degrees ran ſhe aſtray,</l>
               <l>And baniſh't Vertue thus away?</l>
               <l>For <hi>Nemo</hi> (as they ſay with us)</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Repentè ſit Turpiſſimus.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>She cuts her Prayers ſhorter and ſhorter,</l>
               <l>(Perhaps ſhe
<note n="(p)" place="margin">thought</note> weent
<note n="(q)" place="margin">long ones</note> lang yanes wou'd hurt her,)</l>
               <l>And next (what ever ſhou'd betide)</l>
               <l>She fairly lay'd them all aſide.</l>
               <l>Again, ſhe wou'd ha' ſpent haill days,</l>
               <l>In reading damn'd Laſcivious Plays:</l>
               <l>She
<note n="(r)" place="margin">ſung light ſongs,</note> ſang light ſangs, read leud Romances,</l>
               <l>At Night to Balls and wanton Dances.</l>
               <l>She was allow'd an Honeſt Mirth,</l>
               <l>Fit for her Fortune and her Birth;</l>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:98884:23"/>
               <l>But
<note n="(ſ)" place="margin">ſeldom</note> ſeindle now ye can her ſee,</l>
               <l>Out of ſuſpected Company.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>Permitting leſſer Crimes, tho with Remorſe,</l>
               <l>Will ſtain the Conſcience, and make way for worſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>Sir, after this there did
<note n="(t)" place="margin">befall,</note> befaw,</l>
               <l>Another Chop,
<note n="(u)" place="margin">was worſt of all.</note> was warſt of aw.</l>
               <l>Alas! alas! and well-aday!</l>
               <l>It happ'nd on a Haly-day!</l>
               <l>As <hi>Tony</hi> in the Fields was ſtalking,</l>
               <l>And Property
<note n="(m)" place="margin">went</note> gade out a-walking,</l>
               <l>As fine as ever hands cou'd make her,</l>
               <l>He briskly by the Arm did take her,</l>
               <l>And complementally affords</l>
               <l>A pretty parcel of fair Words.</l>
               <l>Sae, finding her a gameſome flirt,</l>
               <l>The winking Thief gave her a <hi>jirt.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He led her back into the
<note n="(x)" place="margin">Hall;</note> Haw,</l>
               <l>And there he play'd her <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p Tails (y) aw.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Now having popp't her Belly
<note n="(z)" place="margin">full,</note> fow,</l>
               <l>And ſill'd her wame up till her
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mouth,</note> mow,</l>
               <l>To chop her off by
<note n="(b)" place="margin">hook or crook,</note> heuk or creuk,</l>
               <l>Was the next Care that <hi>Tony</hi>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">took.</note> teuk.</l>
               <l>A
<note n="(d)" place="margin">A bold inſinuating Sharpen.</note> Swinger
<note n="(e)" place="margin">dwelt</note> won'd about the Court;</l>
               <l>A Lown of very ill report,</l>
               <l>A
<note n="(f)" place="margin">Fulſom Sloven</note> Keuſtran infamouſly famous,</l>
               <l>Knaw'n by the Name of Ignoramus.</l>
               <l>About the Court he had an Office,</l>
               <l>And Sal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry for't that might him ſuffice.</l>
               <l>All that cou'd not his Stomack ſtay,</l>
               <l>But he with baith the hands
<note n="(g)" place="margin">muſt</note> mun play.</l>
               <l>Give him a Greezing in the Firſt,</l>
               <l>He'll hang and ſave juſt as he liſt.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(h)" place="margin">one</note> Yane Night he ſtole the Keys o'th' Priſon</l>
               <l>And ſet thee Thiev's out by the Dozen:</l>
               <l>He cou'd ha' Counterfitted Seal,</l>
               <l>Or forg'd a Deed extreamly weel;</l>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:98884:23"/>
               <l>Sir, lang time he had caſt an Eye,</l>
               <l>At
<note n="(i)" place="margin">very pretty</note> winſom Maiſtriſs Property,</l>
               <l>But ſhe wou'd neither Hyte nor Rhee.</l>
               <l>Now <hi>Tony</hi> found it not a hard ane,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(k)" place="margin">Between</note> Amell them twa to drive a Bargan.</l>
               <l>Sly <hi>Tony</hi> now will try his Art,</l>
               <l>(He
<note n="(l)" place="margin">lov'd</note> leuv'd Miſchief juſt in his Heart:)</l>
               <l>He had a
<note n="(m)" place="margin">falſe Bone</note> faus-bane in his Cheek,</l>
               <l>And
<note n="(n)" place="margin">knew</note> wiſt when, and when not to ſpeak.</l>
               <l>To <hi>Ignoramus</hi> ſlimmy draws,</l>
               <l>And wheadlingly thus op't his <hi>jaws.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dear
<note n="(o)" place="margin">Couſin</note> Keuſin</hi> (for they were o' kinn)</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Faint-heart did nev'r fair Lady winn,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To Property ye were pretender,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I <hi>marvel muckle ye ha' no' gain'd her.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A Man
<note n="(p)" place="margin">ſo</note> ſae ſmart in all your ways,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That the
<note n="(q)" place="margin">whole</note> haill Nation rings your Praiſe:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Perhaps her Modeſty might hinder,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(r)" place="margin">More</note> 
                  <hi>Mair tractable ye now may find her.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Take Courage Man, again
<note n="(ſ)" place="margin">fall</note> faw to,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I ha' done ſike a jobb for you,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(t)" place="margin">So</note> 
                  <hi>Sae feelingly I did her handle,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That on your Knee ye may her dandle.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Quod Ignoramus—Keuſin <hi>Tony,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If thou'lt but help me to my Honey,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If ev'r thine errand ligg i'th' Court,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rely on</hi> Ignoramus <hi>for't.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For thee I'll venture Life, and all</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My Wealth, what e'er come of my
<note n="(u)" place="margin">Soul.</note> Saul.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Quo <hi>Tony</hi> then make haſte—away,</l>
               <l>And
<note n="(x)" place="margin">put on</note> donne thy Haly-day-Array,</l>
               <l>There may be danger in delay.</l>
               <l>The Cull at this, ſae nimble grew,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(y)" place="margin">One</note> Yane wiſt not whether he ran or ſlew.</l>
               <l>He hy'd him up into her Chamber,</l>
               <l>B'ing full aſſur'd to find her tamer;</l>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:98884:24"/>
               <l>There ſhe was raking up and down,</l>
               <l>In Night
<note n="(z)" place="margin">Cloths,</note> Claiths, and her Morning-Gown.</l>
               <l>(For when young Laſſes get ſike Cues,</l>
               <l>Whilk garrs them pewk, and change their hues,</l>
               <l>For better Coll'ring o' the matter,</l>
               <l>And
<note n="(a)" place="margin">from</note> fra the Doctor hide their Water;</l>
               <l>They'll ſay their trouble is this, or that,</l>
               <l>Worms, Tooth-aik, or I knaw not what.)</l>
               <l>Quoth <hi>Ignoramus—now my ſweet,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Here's my four Quarters at your Feet,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>It's no' your
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Portion</note> Togher I account,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tho ye're
<note n="(c)" place="margin">no worſe</note> nae warſe for having on't.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But it's your proper-Perſon-Body,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Turns</hi> Ignoramus <hi>to a Noddy.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alack! when I was in my Fits,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I rav'd like
<note n="(d)" place="margin">one</note> yane out of his Wits:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Rageous Pangs that I ha' tane,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wou'd e'en have burſt'n a Heart o'
<note n="(e)" place="margin">Stone!</note> Stane!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sae take ſome pitty on your
<note n="(f)" place="margin">love;</note> leuve,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And do not ſtill ſae Arſe-ward
<note n="(g)" place="margin">prove</note> preuve.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Now Property began to ponder,</l>
               <l>How ſlyly <hi>Tony</hi> brought her under,</l>
               <l>She
<note n="(h)" place="margin">underſtood</note> underſteud her Market marr'd,</l>
               <l>And of a higher Match debarr'd.</l>
               <l>She did not as ſhe
<note n="(i)" place="margin">uſed</note> wont before,</l>
               <l>Hector and
<note n="(k)" place="margin">ſcold</note> ſcald him out o' Dore;</l>
               <l>But ſoberly forbore her flyting,</l>
               <l>And e'en became the kindeſt Kyting,</l>
               <l>The packeſt thing and the beſt will'd,</l>
               <l>The gentleſt Bird that ever Bill'd.</l>
               <l>When he perceiv'd that he ſhou'd carry'er,</l>
               <l>He made what haſte he cou'd to Marry'er.</l>
               <l>O! how his Heart did
<note n="(l)" place="margin">leap</note> lowp within,</l>
               <l>As ſeun as he the Field did win?</l>
               <l>They pitch upon the
<note n="(m)" place="margin">Marriage</note> Bridal-day,</l>
               <l>(It was no time for her to ſtay.)</l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:98884:24"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>What <hi>holder-forth</hi> was't did the Jobb?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <note n="(n)" place="margin">one</note> Yane that had often
<note n="(o)" place="margin">kiſs't her Mouth.</note> ſmack't her gobb.</l>
               <l>The precious <hi>Salamanca-Doctor,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(Some will no' ſtick to ſay he k—t her)</l>
               <l>And <hi>Tony</hi> mannaged the Sport,</l>
               <l>Juſt in the face o'th' open Court.</l>
               <l>By gazing on Bridegroom and Bride,</l>
               <l>Court buſineſs was laid aſide.</l>
               <l>The Laird cou'd not abide th' affront,</l>
               <l>Nor <hi>Tony</hi> wha was Cauſer on't;</l>
               <l>For
<note n="(p)" place="margin">ſtill the more</note> ay the mair he was forbidd'n,</l>
               <l>He blaſted ſtifflyer at this Wedding.</l>
               <l>Hey-da! How fo'ke did jumble their Tripes,</l>
               <l>When they danc't after <hi>Tony's</hi> Pipes!</l>
               <l>Some gave him
<note n="(q)" place="margin">ſmall pieces of money.</note> placks, and ſome Babbees,</l>
               <l>Some greater, and ſome leſſer Fees.</l>
               <l>The Siſters skew'd their
<note n="(r)" place="margin">Peticoats;</note> Wyly-coats;</l>
               <l>And
<note n="(ſ)" place="margin">ſeldome</note> ſeindle gave him leſs nor Groats:</l>
               <l>Ay, when their heels grew
<note n="(t)" place="margin">ſomewhat</note> ſunckat nimble,</l>
               <l>A Bodkin, or a Siller-Thimble.</l>
               <l>Auld Wives tripp't, aumbling o're the Stanes,</l>
               <l>Tho they were nought but Skins and
<note n="(u)" place="margin">Bones.</note> Banes.</l>
               <l>Some were ſae keen upon the point,</l>
               <l>They danc't their
<note n="(x)" place="margin">Necks</note> Craigs quite out o' Joint.</l>
               <l>There was a ſort of Stomach't younkers,</l>
               <l>Wha ſat them cloſe upon their
<note n="(y)" place="margin">fixt ſeats,</note> bonkers,</l>
               <l>Wi' <hi>Tory</hi>-Ribbons in their Bonnets,</l>
               <l>And
<note n="(z)" place="margin">always</note> ayle they skowld at <hi>Tony's</hi> Sonnets:</l>
               <l>They ſhak't their Snouts, and ſtamp't like Madd;</l>
               <l>At laſt ſpeak's out a Mettall'd Ladd:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I thought we'ad other tow to teeze,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nor ſee this Lown-like Lordan ſqueene</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Greezy</note> Creeſhy-baggs, and Laugh, and Fleer,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And o'er the Comp'ny domineer,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As if he were a Noble Peer.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:98884:25"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Our Maiſter will be out o' patience,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If we
<note n="(b)" place="margin">neglect</note> miſlippne his occaſions.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He
<note n="(c)" place="margin">know's</note> kens (for he is nae unwiſe one),</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(d)" place="margin">Which</note> 
                  <hi>Whilk ſide of's Bread his Butter ly's on,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He pays us
<note n="(e)" place="margin">Wages</note> Fee, and finds us
<note n="(f)" place="margin">Clothing,</note> Cleathing,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As honeſtly as
<note n="(g)" place="margin">any</note> ony Breathing.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For Belly-Timber I will ſwear it,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>(If aw the Warld were here to hear it)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>There's Beef, and Mutton, Veal and Bacon,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gooſe, Rabbit, Turky, Hen and Capon,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sae Fat, ſae Faire (thanks be to God)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(h)" place="margin">makes</note> 
                  <hi>Garrs all our Grinders gang Wet-ſhod.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ye may ſit down, and eat, and fill ye,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Till ye can
<note n="(i)" place="margin">make your Belly's ſtiff as a board.</note> crack a Louſe on Belly;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And cramm your
<note n="(k)" place="margin">Bellys</note> Kytes wi' Meat and Drink,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then ſafely tumble, and take a wink,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And
<note n="(l)" place="margin">ſince</note> ſen we are thus kindly us'd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let not
<note n="(m)" place="margin">good</note> geud Nature be abus'd.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Or if we ſhou'd (as others do)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To Horſe-Race, Fair, or
<note n="(n)" place="margin">Annual Feaſts in Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Towns where no Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket is kep't.</note> Hoppin go,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>There play our caſts amang the Whipſters,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Throw for the Hammer,
<note n="(o)" place="margin">leap</note> lowp for Slippers,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And ſee the Maids Dance for the Ring,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Or any other pleaſant thing;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(p)" place="margin">Lying for the Whetſtone, I'm told, has been practiz'd, but Farting for the Pigg is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Memory of any Imet with; tho it's a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-phraſe in the North, to any that's well gift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that way; and probable there has been ſuch a mad practice formerly.</note> 
                  <hi>Fart for the Pigg, lye for the Whet-ſtone,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Or chuſe what ſide to lay our betts on:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If we but carry't decently,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He nev'r ſays yance—Black's your Eye.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We ha' the Warld faſt in a band,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And the bands end juſt in our hand.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Or gin we chance, through Humane Frailty,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To meet a Laſs and give her
<note n="(q)" place="margin">Perſuade one to't tho un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing.</note> Kelty,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And popp her fow, as in ſike Caſes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Is us'd about your great Mens places;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Or if we to the Ale-houſe go,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And get a Pot i'th' Pate, or ſo</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:98884:25"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Or Bairns fall out at handy-dandy,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He e'en forgives as faſt as can be.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Speak Truth, and nev'r belye your Lips,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Has not ſome here oft miſs't their Whips?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I'm ſure were he not tender-hearted,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Some of your Tails had ſoundly ſmarted.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And ſince that he treats us ſae Nobly,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let us be mindful of the Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(ſ)" place="margin">which</note> 
                  <hi>whilk tye us unto him,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And for mair of his leuve to wooe him.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For Clemency
<note n="(t)" place="margin">none</note> nane can out-vy'm,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Yet rowze not up a ſleeping Lyon.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The De'il (God I beteach me to)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I think has gott'n a gripp o' you!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That can, and will no' live in Peace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But follow out ſyke freaks as theſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Leuk but a bit beyond the
<note n="(u)" place="margin">Strand, or Brook,</note> Beck,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And then I here will pawn my Neck,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(x)" place="margin">No people in the World ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in priviledges as our King's Subjects.</note> 
                  <hi>If ony of the Neigh'b'ring Lairds,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ev'r gave their Servants ſike Rewards.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They dare no' call their Sauls their
<note n="(y)" place="margin">own.</note> ain,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>What miſchief then garrs us Complain?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Here's ſike a deal of Ribble-rabble,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wi'</hi> Tony <hi>and his ſqueeking Babble,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As if the
<note n="(z)" place="margin">ſcalp</note> pow of ſtinking <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rchin</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Were a ſit neſt to hatch a Church in.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Our time ſhou'd no' this way be ſpent;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let's get our Maiſter in his Rent.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tho' he has meikle uſe for Money,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We take no thought to get him ony.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let us make up the Caſtle
<note n="(a)" place="margin">walls,</note> waws,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And keep them right what e'er
<note n="(b)" place="margin">befalls;</note> befaws;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If aw the reſt were right repair'd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I trow our Labour were well
<note n="(c)" place="margin">beſtow'd.</note> wair'd.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>(For if his
<note n="(d)" place="margin">dwelling-houſe.</note> place be weak and thin,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Some wyly Thieves may
<note n="(e)" place="margin">ſoon</note> ſeun creep in:</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:98884:26"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>They'll
<note n="(f)" place="margin">rob him</note> reave his geuds if they can find 'em,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And trow ye they'll leave ours behind 'em?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nev'r
<note n="(g)" place="margin">look for't.</note> leuk for't, De'il a doubt they're in,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But they'll
<note n="(h)" place="margin">go</note> gang on when they begin.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They'll make their awn what e'er they get,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>There's nought but Fiſh comes in their Net.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Plaiſter, ſecure, and make
<note n="(i)" place="margin">all</note> aw ſtrang,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They'll ſerve him and his Followers lang;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(k)" place="margin">If</note> 
                  <hi>Gin we ſlight him, our ſel's we wrang.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And what perteens no' to our ſhare,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let other Servants take in care.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>There is a ſort of uſeful Wherrys,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That do geud Service in our Ferrys:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let them be rigg'd and rightly mann'd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then they'll he ready at Command,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To ſend to th' Market and fetch hame,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Proviſion
<note n="(l)" place="margin">b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>th</note> baith for Back and
<note n="(m)" place="margin">Belly.</note> Wame.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And gaudy Trinkats for our Wives,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>(Elſe we will lead but Helliſh lives</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If of their Pride they want a Pin,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>De'il be i'their Tongues if ev'r they blin.)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Do but obſerve yon' greedy Youths,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wha eat the Meat out of our Mouths;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(n)" place="margin">Thoſe</note> 
                  <hi>Thea Glutt'nous Hoghen-Moghen Hounds,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Steal aw the Fiſh out of our Ponds.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They're ſneaking ſtill about our Towns,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And oft attempt to Crack our Crowns.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(o)" place="margin">Reprove</note> 
                  <hi>Repreuve them for't, and
<note n="(p)" place="margin">ev'ry.</note> ilka Widgeon,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Will vaunt—A through-reform'd Religion.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But if
<note n="(q)" place="margin">ſuch</note> ſyke priviledge can do,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They'll labber in our Swine-troughs too.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Prepare, and if they
<note n="(r)" place="margin">once</note> yance begin,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We'll
<note n="(ſ)" place="margin">ſoon</note> ſeun ſouſe up</hi> Van-Souterkin.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We'll learn them other ways to feed,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nor lick the Butter off our Bread.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:98884:26"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Yon
<note n="(t)" place="margin">One juſt rip for the Gallows</note> hang-a bauk,
<note n="(u)" place="margin">yeſterday</note> yeſt day at Morn</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Swore
<note n="(x)" place="margin">Sham-plot</note> aw the
<note n="(y)" place="margin">Cattle</note> Nout was in the Corn,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They've pinded ſome, they have nae Straw,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If they bide
<note n="(z)" place="margin">long,</note> lang, their Chafts will
<note n="(a)" place="margin">fall.</note> faw.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I've ſought the Field fra end to end,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>There's nathing hurt that God did ſend:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>An' truth were kenn'd, I think i' faith,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>It is their awn will do the
<note n="(b)" place="margin">harm;</note> skaith;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They're leuking where to find a
<note n="(c)" place="margin">35th. <hi>of Q.</hi> Eliz. <hi>to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal'd.</hi>
                     </note> gapp.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And if they find it in they'll ſlapp.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With their
<note n="(d)" place="margin">crook't</note> creuk't Horns they marr the Dyke,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Forſeuth I did but
<note n="(e)" place="margin">put the Law in Execution;</note> hound the Tyke.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Out came a drift of curſt thraw'n Fellows,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>(They're fit for nathing but the Gallows)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Had not ſome help't, there is nae doubt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(f)" place="margin">Loyal-Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</note> 
                  <hi>But there they'd
<note n="(g)" place="margin">beat out my Brains.</note> dung my peur harns out.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We ſerve not God by Brags and Ranting,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As if we met a Covenanting;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Or if there were nae King amang us,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Except his Majeſty'</hi> Ignoramus.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>What—? ha' we nathing to do here,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But
<note n="(h)" place="margin">Excluſion</note> pipe fo'ke fra their lawfow geer?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ye ſhou'd conſider'd wha ye
<note n="(i)" place="margin">meddl'd.</note> mell'd with,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Before ſyke Doctrine firſt was held-forth.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Be't knaw'n, he is no back-deur-Chick,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nor will he be ſerv'd ſike a Trick:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He crav's nae mair but what's his due,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>By right of Dad, and Bully too.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They'll wonder what a de'il we ayle,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To ſea'd our Lipps in other's kale:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let us do what
<note n="(k)" place="margin">belongs</note> perteens to us;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Our Maiſter weel can rule his Houſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(l)" place="margin">tear all to pieces,</note> 
                  <hi>Ryve aw to Raggs, and then ye kenn,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>When doors ſtand open, Dogs come
<note n="(m)" place="margin">into the houſe:</note> ben:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>This ſhall be ſcan'd before our
<note n="(n)" place="margin">Lords,</note> Betters,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Or els my Carcaſs liggs in Fetters.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:98884:27"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Remember
<note n="(m)" place="margin">many</note> mony years by-gane,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>When he that rul'd us Right was ſlain;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Reſpect to Quality was loſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tinkers, and Coblers rul'd the roſt:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Nobles were the Common's Cadgers,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Gentry but the Soldiers Badgers;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And ſae far'd we, fra ill to worſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>When Cart was ſet before the Horſe.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>How many brave and gallant Families,</l>
               <l>Have been deſtroy'd by 'ſpouſing Treacheries?</l>
               <l>Their Children, and their Children's Children groan</l>
               <l>Under that Load, their Rebel-Sires laid on.</l>
               <l>Their Coats of Arms defac'd in publick view,</l>
               <l>Their Progeny rank'd with the ſervile Crew.</l>
               <l>Should I take Meaſures from that dire Succeſs,</l>
               <l>Mine Off Spring and their Heirs wou'd bear no leſs.</l>
               <l>The bleſſed <hi>Jeſus</hi> gave his own Example,</l>
               <l>(Which none of us ought under foot to trample)</l>
               <l>He pay'd a Tribute to Uſurping Prince,</l>
               <l>Not as his <hi>due;</hi>) for how could that be, ſince</l>
               <l>Himſelf was Lord of all,) but that we might</l>
               <l>Be taught to give both God, and <hi>Caeſar</hi> Right?</l>
               <l>His Poverty allow'd him not the Coin,</l>
               <l>Therefore he did with bleſſed <hi>Peter</hi> join:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Go fiſh the Summ, that all the World may ſee</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Pattern of it's God's Humility.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Here's no Contingency, for what I do,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I'll re-inforce by Miracle to you.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"Shall <hi>Jeſus,</hi> Powerful <hi>Jeſus</hi> work in vain,</l>
               <l>"To guide our Steps, and wretched we disdain</l>
               <l>"To follow him? O wonder! wonder! ſince</l>
               <l>"Our Soveraign's Claim is no unjuſt Pretence.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>Sir I's but weak when rightly reckon'd,</l>
               <l>Your geud Diſcourſe I canno' ſecond;</l>
               <l>But there is manny' a worthy Man,</l>
               <l>In <hi>Scotland</hi> bred, wha right well can:</l>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:98884:27"/>
               <l>Therefore I' ad beſt keep mine awn road,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>Do ſo, go on i'th' name of God.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>A dancer ſays, fra' amang the reſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>This Land of ours is ſare oppreſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Our Grievances ſhall be redreſt.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What are
<note n="(n)" place="margin">theſe</note> thea Grievances? let's ſee?</l>
               <l>Alas! alas! and
<note n="(o)" place="margin">woe's me!</note> wae's is me!</l>
               <l>Peur <hi>Nob's</hi> condemn'd to Gallow-Tree.</l>
               <l>What was the reaſon? ſpeak wha can?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He was a witty wary Man.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Cou'd Whiggs got ſike a
<note n="(p)" place="margin">ſpoak</note> ſpaik in wheel,</l>
               <l>Their Cauſe had not ſae
<note n="(q)" place="margin">ſoon</note> ſeun tane reel.</l>
               <l>Whig Writers are (gi' them their due)</l>
               <l>As ſcant of Wit, as Grace, I trow.</l>
               <l>Let no Man call me lying Fellow,</l>
               <l>'Till he reads <hi>Sh— Tegue-Devillo;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He calls it Witch, for Witch we had it,</l>
               <l>E'en
<note n="(r)" place="margin">ſuch</note> ſike a Witch as he that made it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>Had I of Plays ten Thouſand to rehearſe,</l>
               <l>If all were his, they nev'r cou'd make a Farce.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>But mair nor that, his Lordſhip itches</l>
               <l>To baniſh Papiſh Dogs and Bitches:</l>
               <l>He has geud reaſon to take heed,</l>
               <l>For ſpoiling true proteſting-Breed.</l>
               <l>And further ſtill I can aſſure ye,</l>
               <l>Chitt-Pus canno' eſcape his fury.</l>
               <l>Shou'd Pop'ry worm into his Mice,</l>
               <l>He'll find that but a blind Device.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>Some deſp'rate Men, who know not how to live,</l>
               <l>Or baſe-born-Slaves cannot ſo much deceive;</l>
               <l>But for the upper-rank to ſtake to nought,</l>
               <l>That mighty All their Anceſtors have bought,</l>
               <l>With Blood and Wounds, and puiſſant Service done,</l>
               <l>Muſt be miraculous to ev'ry one!</l>
               <l>Let's now forbear, we are not throng,</l>
               <l>We may be dry, we've talk't ſo long.</l>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:98884:28"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Here Boy—a Bottle more of Claret.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The tother Health, our Brains will bear it,</l>
               <l>God bleſs the King, and Queen.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>Drink off your Glaſs, and to't agen.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>Now this has chop't me by my Text,</l>
               <l>Ho—now I think on't—this is next.</l>
               <l>There was a Sett of Dancers came,</l>
               <l>But few of them I right can Name.</l>
               <l>Firſt <hi>Perkin,</hi> O! he dances trimly,</l>
               <l>And turn's on heel, and
<note n="(ſ)" place="margin">tiptoes</note> tiptaes nimbly!</l>
               <l>He is, (as mony fo'ke believes)</l>
               <l>An able Fellow of his
<note n="(t)" place="margin">Hands,</note> Neev's,</l>
               <l>In ſundry places had he been,</l>
               <l>And cruel Bickerings had he ſeen,</l>
               <l>Still he his ſel' ſae weell hehav'd,</l>
               <l>You'd ſworn <hi>God-Mars</hi> was newly ſhav'd.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(u)" place="margin">Both</note> Baith Man, and Lad at the ſame inſtant;</l>
               <l>But Fortune, well-away's unconſtant,</l>
               <l>He kep't his ſel' ſae marv'llous buſie,</l>
               <l>Until his Head grew reeling dizzie;</l>
               <l>At laſt he catch't a heavy
<note n="(x)" place="margin">fall,</note> faw,</l>
               <l>And there lay he for geud and
<note n="(y)" place="margin">all.</note> aw.</l>
               <l>Yet notwithſtanding this Confuſion,</l>
               <l>Turn'd <hi>Hoghen-Moghen</hi> in Concluſion:</l>
               <l>If nought will ſerve but <hi>Belgick-bouts,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Beleuv'd, take up your King of Clouts.</l>
               <l>Sir
<note n="(z)" place="margin">2d Dancer</note> ne'er-do-well, Squire Brazen-Face,</l>
               <l>Mufty, <hi>Maiſt-John</hi> ſcant of Gods Grace,</l>
               <l>A ſqueeking Treble, yet nought but Baſe.</l>
               <l>A <hi>Teckley</hi> for the Chriſtians loſs,</l>
               <l>And bears the Creſtent for the Croſs:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Buggery,</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Hic-haec-Conjunx, Jack</hi> of <hi>Leyden,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Brother Looſe-down, Siſter Slyding,</l>
               <l>In plenty
<note n="(b)" place="margin">poor,</note> peur, but rich in want;</l>
               <l>A voucher of the Covenant.</l>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:98884:28"/>
               <l>Girdl'd, and Sworded, flail'd new Faſhion,</l>
               <l>Saviour, Damner of the Nation,</l>
               <l>Jeſuit, and Prieſt Canonical,</l>
               <l>A Heathen, Chriſtian, Devil and all.</l>
               <l>Theſe are his Names, and I'll be ſworn,</l>
               <l>Nae <hi>Spaniard</hi> has
<note n="(c)" place="margin">ſo many</note> ſae mony worn.</l>
               <l>He capers high as Royal Gallery,</l>
               <l>And next ſteps back into the Pillory.</l>
               <l>He had mae
<note n="(d)" place="margin">Ears</note> lugs when time befell</l>
               <l>Of other fo'k's, nor tongue can tell;</l>
               <l>But now he ſcarce has
<note n="(e)" place="margin">one</note> yane his ſel'.</l>
               <l>Latin he ſpeaks at
<note n="(f)" place="margin">ev'ry</note> ilka Sentence,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Don John</hi>'s familiar Acquaintance,</l>
               <l>He knew his dark Complexion well,</l>
               <l>Yet made him fair by Art and Skill:</l>
               <l>Tho' he and others of that Breed,</l>
               <l>Made <hi>Stafford</hi> ſhorter by the Head,</l>
               <l>His Wit's now of that pregnant ſtrength,</l>
               <l>It ſpins <hi>Don-John</hi> ſax-feet of length.</l>
               <l>The Cauſe's Trumpeters and Fiddlers,</l>
               <l>Officious Coxcombs and State-Jugglers,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Aarons,</hi> and Spiritual Higglers,</l>
               <l>Parliament and Petition ſticklers,</l>
               <l>The Maid of <hi>Hatfield</hi> and the Wheadlers,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Care, Curtis,</hi> and the <hi>Elephant,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Danc't till their very: Hearts did pant.</l>
               <l>The
<note n="(g)" place="margin">Eves-drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,</note> Lythning-Liſtners, with their leering,</l>
               <l>Nor Fiſh, nor Fleſh, nor geud Red-Herring,</l>
               <l>They caper'd not, but
<note n="(h)" place="margin">ſmoothly</note> ſmeuthly <hi>jimm'd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Like ſome I knaw on, when they <hi>trimm'd.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The chiefeſt Art that Trimmers know,</l>
               <l>Is twiſting twa Strings for a Bow.</l>
               <l>The Pamphleteering-Libelling-Train,</l>
               <l>They ſtirr'd them till they ſtunk again.</l>
               <l>Ye wou'd ha' burſtne your Heart wi' laughing,</l>
               <l>To've ſeen the gang ſae full o'daffing.</l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:98884:29"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>Vex, vex me not with that vile ſpurious Tribe,</l>
               <l>Which Satyriſm it ſelf can nev'r deſcribe.</l>
               <l>Or why ſhould I this harmleſs Page beſpatter,</l>
               <l>With any <hi>Judas patriae Liberator?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or what can Piety't ſelf expect but Evil,</l>
               <l>From <hi>Symon Magus</hi> Chaplain to the Devil?</l>
               <l>There is no tracing thee, but to that Flame,</l>
               <l>From whence thou and thy Damn'd Tap't Patron came?</l>
               <l>Was there ſuch Reliſh in thy Sov'raigns Blood,</l>
               <l>To long for it, when Heav'n it ſelf withſtood?</l>
               <l>To ſtately <hi>Charles</hi> the top of Royal Stem,</l>
               <l>(Whoſe frontly Brow adorn'd the Diadem,</l>
               <l>Whoſe Exequies in ſilent Breaſt will throb,</l>
               <l>Tho his Succeſſor periods the Sob)</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">New-Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket.</note> A Fire on Earth did once great favour ſhew,</l>
               <l>But Fire in Hell will thee (falſe Prieſt) purſue,</l>
               <l>Unleſs thou Modelize thy Life anew.</l>
               <l>Thou put'ſt not off thy Treaſons by Retail,</l>
               <l>No, thou'rt a Trades-man only for Whole-ſale:</l>
               <l>Thy Bart'ring Mart can readily diſpatch</l>
               <l>The Royal <hi>Cargo,</hi>—off with ſtock and ſwatch.</l>
               <l>Had but thy Native ſoil thine <hi>Equal bred,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cleav'land</hi>'s ſharp Satyrs had been blunt indeed.</l>
               <l>Raſh muſe! what ha'ſt thou done? his <hi>Equal</hi>'s come,</l>
               <l>Avant Curſt Pedagogue, Curſt in the Womb,</l>
               <l>Curſt all thy Life, and Curſed in thy Tomb.</l>
               <l>But Curſter ſtill, and Curſter than before,</l>
               <l>Becauſe there is no Curſe for thee in ſtore;</l>
               <l>God, Angels, Men, and Devils can Curſe no more</l>
               <l>Than thou haſt Curſt thy ſelf on <hi>Julian</hi>'s ſcore.</l>
               <l>Did not the hideous forms of thy foul Brat,</l>
               <l>(Foul as that Fiend, which prompting by thee ſat,</l>
               <l>Black as thy Sin, ſuperlativ'ly ill,</l>
               <l>Black as the Poyſon of thy Ven'mous Quill:</l>
               <l>Foul as that Soul was fair, which thou endeavour'd</l>
               <l>(Oh! vain attempt!) to've made appear ill-favour'd.)</l>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:98884:29"/>
               <l>Did not, I ſay, that Lucifugeous face,</l>
               <l>A baſer Soul from thy baſe Body chace?</l>
               <l>Did not thy Lines, when crawling forth they came,</l>
               <l>Gnaw out the Intrails of their Vip'rous Dam?</l>
               <l>No—Heav'n for Secret Cauſe lent thee ſome time,</l>
               <l>Or to atone, or to enlarge thy Crime.</l>
               <l>Sift Earth, Rake H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll, ſearch the Creation round,</l>
               <l>With Angels eyes, tell me where can be found</l>
               <l>Legions of Plagues, but in that Plaguy Race</l>
               <l>Which can both Heav'n, and Earth and Hell out-face;</l>
               <l>Were God, not God, he cou'd not grant them Grace.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>Here aw the Comp'ny went away,</l>
               <l>And left it till another day.</l>
               <l>Geud reaſon why, they durſt not ſtay.</l>
               <l>Sae having tane a little Breath,</l>
               <l>Fell to it, Dagger out of Sheath.</l>
               <l>Again ſpeaks out a
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Active,</note> Lyver-lad,</l>
               <l>A truſty <hi>Trojan,</hi> thus he ſaid.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">Oath of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance.</note> 
                  <hi>Did we not pawn Body and Saul,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Our Maiſter to defend and all</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Comes after him, ſae
<note n="(d)" place="margin">long as</note> lang's we live?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And do ye think God will forgive?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If we run wilfully in Sin,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Judge ye what pickle we ſhall be in.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ha' ye nae fear of God nor Man,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But work miſchief e'en what ye can?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Turn out o'
<note n="(e)" place="margin">door</note> deur this ſtinking Jack-an-</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>apes; where he but ſet a packing,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>You wou'd no' bob ſae
<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                        <hi>The Exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion Bill was their Sunday</hi>'s <hi>work, for the moſt part:</hi> The better day, the better deed.</note> on the Sunday,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>It's nae imployment for God's awn day.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wou'd ever any Man or Woman,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(g)" place="margin">Break the line of Succeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> 
                  <hi>Turn Free-hold into Enter-Common?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Or ſlay the herds wha his Lambs keep?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The
<note n="(h)" place="margin">Fox</note> Todd will worry aw the Sheep:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Or wry about the Neck o'th' Cock?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Glead will get the Chicken-Flock.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:98884:30"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Or break a gap in his
<note n="(i)" place="margin">own</note> awn fence?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>When certain to his ſad expence,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Beaſts will ſlip into his Corn,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His Neighbours will laugh him to ſcorn.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Many have had fair Pleas and loſt 'em,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>By fondly breaking of thier Cuſtom.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Twou'd vex a man to th' very Guts,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To ſit ſeaven year, cracking deaf Nuts.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(k)" place="margin">Act of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion.</note> 
                  <hi>Mind what the Loyal Scotch-men ſay,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If we dance on ſae will not they.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then will begin ſike Broyls and Tuggs,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And
<note n="(l)" place="margin">cuffing</note> lund'ring yane anothers Luggs,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fy, out for ſhame it ſhou'd be ſpoken,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They'll
<note n="(m)" place="margin">curſe</note> ban us when we're Dead and Rotten.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The
<note n="(n)" place="margin">Warld</note> Warld will think us dev'liſh Wanton,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Still hobbling after Piper</hi> Anthon.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sir, here's a
<note n="(o)" place="margin">A Fellow all-moſt at his growth.</note> Spaught that came fra</hi> Taunton.</l>
               <l>After a Godly Grimace made,</l>
               <l>He paus'd, and ſpit, and thus he ſaid.</l>
               <l>"I ſwear if <hi>Tony</hi> pipe not on,</l>
               <l>"The Subject's Property is gone.</l>
               <l>"Let's now lift up our Godly Paws,</l>
               <l>"And mannage well the Geud Auld Cauſe:</l>
               <l>"If Conſcience be our hinderance,</l>
               <l>"Our <hi>Anarchy</hi> will nev'r advance.</l>
               <l>"Shou'd we be ty'd to fond <hi>Punctilio's,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"'Twere
<note n="(p)" place="margin">worſe</note> warſe nor Papiſh <hi>Tormentilio's.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"Come <hi>Tony</hi>—Play—thou knaw'ſt my Jigg,</l>
               <l>"I'll take my turn, and then a Figg</l>
               <l>"For ony Cavalieriſh Pigg.</l>
               <l>"There's Law, Religion, in thy Chanter,</l>
               <l>"
<note n="(q)" place="margin">More</note> Mair nor they knaw on, <hi>ſo I'll venture.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"Shall we make
<note n="(r)" place="margin">Fools</note> Feuls of Hands and Feet,</l>
               <l>"And they ſit Laughing in that Seat?</l>
               <l>"Mumping and
<note n="(ſ)" place="margin">looking as if they wou'd bite.</note> Mowing, making Faces,</l>
               <l>"Doing their outmoſt to diſgrace us.</l>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:98884:30"/>
               <l>"Let them take warning, I'll take courſe,</l>
               <l>"If they'll not dance they ſhall do worſe.</l>
               <l>"We'll flail them into better Manners,</l>
               <l>"And ſell their skins to Godly Tanners;</l>
               <l>"Or if we ſtop them well wi' Straw,</l>
               <l>"They'll
<note n="(t)" place="margin">fright</note> fley the <hi>Tory's</hi> all
<note n="(u)" place="margin">away.</note> awaw.</l>
               <l>"I gueſs they've heard what
<note n="(x)" place="margin">No Po. Succeſsor.</note> this days Vote is,</l>
               <l>"We'll
<note n="(y)" place="margin">bang their Coats,</note> paik their Hides, let them take notice.</l>
               <l>"They may expect, but find nae Quarters,</l>
               <l>"We'll make their very Guts their Garters:</l>
               <l>"They canno' ſay but I ha' warn'd 'em;</l>
               <l>Yet ſtill they parted and nae harm done.</l>
               <l>Where
<note n="(z)" place="margin">one</note> yane ſaid—<hi>Tony</hi>—Gang thy way,</l>
               <l>There ſtill was three cry'd—Let him ſtay:</l>
               <l>And he for
<note n="(a)" place="margin">all thoſe</note> aw thea Brags and Cracks,</l>
               <l>Still rumbled on behind their Backs.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">Unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</note> Unſonſy
<note n="(c)" place="margin">once,</note> yance,
<note n="(d)" place="margin">unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</note> unſonſy
<note n="(e)" place="margin">always</note> aye,</l>
               <l>We'll hear of this ſome-other day;</l>
               <l>The Halter lang they canno' 'ſcape;</l>
               <l>They'll hang themſel's gi' them but
<note n="(f)" place="margin">Rope.</note> Raip.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>Come—drink to me—, do't—I'll ingage ye,</l>
               <l>Begin—ſpeak,—Chriſten't, I will pledge ye:</l>
               <l>I'm not inclin'd to rant and tear,</l>
               <l>But yet this day, we being here,</l>
               <l>May take a Bumper jollily.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>God bleſs the Royal Family.</l>
               <l>Lang-laſt the Court remeuv'd to <hi>Oxford,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where there had like to ha'been knocks for't:</l>
               <l>Another
<note n="(g)" place="margin">looſe Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</note> Taiſtril with them came,</l>
               <l>And he play'd ſweetly on the <hi>ſhaum,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Here's
<note n="(h)" place="margin">ev'ry one</note> ilka yane better nor other,</l>
               <l>But
<note n="(i)" place="margin">wonder</note> whaw—! how they hit on together;</l>
               <l>The Rabble-rowt ſae whew'd and whirl'd,</l>
               <l>When Pipe and Shaum togither skirl'd.</l>
               <l>That Gentleman of high eſteem,</l>
               <l>(Indeed their Maiſter ſhou'd ha' been,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(k)" place="margin">who</note> Wha did no'
<note n="(l)" place="margin">love</note> leuve to hear them skreem,)</l>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:98884:31"/>
               <l>Wha was a geud-ane and a great-ane,</l>
               <l>And by his ſtile the <hi>Laird of Britain.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Sir, he had warn'd them oft before,</l>
               <l>But De'il a byte wou'd they give o'er.</l>
               <l>Nor ſhame a Spring wou'd
<note n="(m)" place="margin">thoſe two</note> thea twa play,</l>
               <l>Except <hi>the clean contrary way.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He
<note n="(n)" place="margin">took</note> teuk a
<note n="(o)" place="margin">Scepter</note> Sweeple up in's
<note n="(p)" place="margin">hand,</note> neef,</l>
               <l>Quoth he to <hi>Tony</hi>—"<hi>Squinting Thief,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"<hi>Have I ſav'd thee thrice fra the
<note n="(q)" place="margin">Gallows,</note> Widdy.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"<hi>To
<note n="(r)" place="margin">make</note> garr my folke run
<note n="(ſ)" place="margin">ſtark mad?</note> Hiddy-giddy?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"<hi>I'll make (unleſs thou leave this Game,)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"<hi>Thy Back as
<note n="(t)" place="margin">break all thy Bones.</note> ſupple as thy Wame.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"<hi>What
<note n="(u)" place="margin">diſorderly noiſe</note> hirdy girdy's this ye keep?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"<hi>I canno' get a wink o' ſleep.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"<hi>'T has been the hail courſe of thy Life,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"<hi>To pipe thy Neighbours into ſtrife;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"<hi>By haunting Coffee-houſe and Ale-houſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"<hi>Thou trains their Bairns up to the Gallows.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"<hi>Syke
<note n="(x)" place="margin">needleſs ſtir</note> dirdom 'tween thy Pipes and thee,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"<hi>And ayllway's when they take the
<note n="(y)" place="margin">grow reſtiff,</note> gee,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"<hi>Thou thinks to make a Feul o' me!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"Do'ſt thou not know I qou'd undone thee,</l>
               <l>"And ſtill put'ſt thou thy Pranks upon me?</l>
               <l>"Gang on—in ſpight o' thy baſe mind,</l>
               <l>"I'll preuve thy Maiſter, thou ſhalt find.</l>
               <l>"Ingratfow Monſter kenn thy ſel';</l>
               <l>"For thou'rt juſt like the Fiend of Hell;</l>
               <l>"God made him great and he rebell'd,</l>
               <l>"Sik-like my Geudneſs has thee ſwell'd:</l>
               <l>"
<note n="(z)" place="margin">Since</note> Sen I ſet thee to
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Chancellor</note> Seal my Letters,</l>
               <l>"Thou
<note n="(b)" place="margin">always</note> aylways has
<note n="(c)" place="margin">diſown<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> miskenn'd thy Betters.</l>
               <l>"Leave off, or elſe I tell thee plain,</l>
               <l>"
<note n="(d)" place="margin">beat out all thy Brains</note> I'll garr thy harns jaip again:</l>
               <l>"Nor is't for aw that I command it,</l>
               <l>"It's but thy Duty—<hi>underſtand it.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He might as well talk't to a
<note n="(e)" place="margin">Stone,</note> ſtane,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Tony</hi> e'en blew up again,</l>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:98884:31"/>
               <l>And blew as if 't had been his laſt,</l>
               <l>And
<note n="(f)" place="margin">ſtrein'd himſelf,</note> pegh't,
<note n="(g)" place="margin">groan'd.</note> and grain'd at ilka blaſt.</l>
               <l>He frisks, he ſtruts, and bobs about,</l>
               <l>His Een was like to've poppled out.</l>
               <l>Sir, then the Gentl'man whilk I ſpoke on,</l>
               <l>Reſolv'd his Pipes ſhou'd aw be broken.</l>
               <l>He came upon him ere he wiſt,</l>
               <l>(And as I gueſs he did no miſs't)</l>
               <l>As <hi>Tony</hi> Bag-pipe ſtiffly ſqueezes;</l>
               <l>He ſmaſh't them in five hundred pieces.</l>
               <l>Had ye ſeen what a
<note n="(a)" place="margin">look he look't,</note> leuk he leuk't,</l>
               <l>And in what Dudgeon <hi>Tony</hi> teuk't,</l>
               <l>Ye wou'd
<note n="(b)" place="margin">almoſt</note> amaiſt ha' pitty'd him;</l>
               <l>His Maiſter ſae out-witted him.</l>
               <l>He gruntl'd lyke a Sow wi' Piggs,</l>
               <l>Say's to his ſel'—<hi>Now aw my Jiggs,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And Jigging-bobs are laid aſide,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Their Lace, their Ribbons, and their Pride,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And aw the Wit in</hi> Tony's <hi>Noddle,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Will never make them worth a boddle.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And was not this a
<note n="(c)" place="margin">ſere</note> ſare miſchance!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>E'en juſt as they began to Dance,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To play me ſike a ſurly Trick,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I nev'r ſaw like ſen I was quiok.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I think indeed that I was
<note n="(d)" place="margin">Fooliſh,</note> Daft,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>When I fell to this Piper Craft.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But yet I had a gay Report,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In City, Country, and at Court.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wi' muckle a-doe I got a pair</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of Pipes, alas my Heart is ſare,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To ſee them Ligg in Splinters there!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A truer Pipe nev'r went wi' Wind,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And it was tun'd juſt to my mind;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alas! I never did intend,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They ſhou'd ha' made this doleful end.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I'll never be
<note n="(e)" place="margin">able.</note> yable, with aw my Care,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To purchaſe ſike another pair.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:98884:32"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Had they but danc't a little while,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I think I cou'd ha' drop't a wyle,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To have play'd ſome of them a ſleep;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But aw my Cues I now may keep;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I canno' ſee them but I weep.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He try'd his Art by might and main,</l>
               <l>But nev'r cou'd Tune them up again:</l>
               <l>The Reeds a little while did ſneevle,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(f)" place="margin">Then</note> Syne Dron's, and aw ran to the Devil.</l>
               <l>The fright, the fury, and the ſhame,</l>
               <l>Diſpatch'd him off by <hi>Amſterdam.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Sir, will ye hear his <hi>Epitaph?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I fancy it may
<note n="(g)" place="margin">make</note> garre ye laugh.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Beneath this ſtane ly's Mankind's Wonder,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>('Pray God its weight may keep him under.)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He was a Fowl of
<note n="(h)" place="margin">ſuch</note> ſike a Feather,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He nev'r cou'd fly but in foul Weather.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(i)" place="margin">All, and all,</note> 
                  <hi>Top, Tail, and Main of ilka Faction,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The
<note n="(k)" place="margin">a Child's Play-tool, turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing always round in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Motions.</note> Whirlygeeg of Humane Action.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A very dangerous twa-edg'd
<note n="(l)" place="margin">Tool,</note> Teul,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His Wit made him
<note n="(m)" place="margin">both</note> baith Knave and
<note n="(n)" place="margin">Fool.</note> Feul:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A Cellar and a Ware-Houſe baith,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To all wha Trade in publick Faith:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He brew'd, and tap'd, and ſqueez'd and ran,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>At laſt, as faſt as he began;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But dabbl'd ſtill in ſike ſtumm'd Liquor,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The De'il himſel' ne'er piſs't a thicker.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Noddy Knave of Common-weal,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He ſhuffl'd oft, but never cou'd deal.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He ſtaik't his Craig, or ony thing,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And play'd at piquet with the King.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>All Arts and Myſteries he try'd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But nev'r wrought truly till he dy'd.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He's dead and gane, we need no fear,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As ſure as he is lying here.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:98884:32"/>
               <l>The Shaum a while eſcap't the fury,</l>
               <l>By ſleight of <hi>Ignoramus-Jury:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But after (as appeared plain)</l>
               <l>They call'd him o'er the Coals again,</l>
               <l>And to the beſt part of my kno'ledge,</l>
               <l>Some ru'd the rade of <hi>Oxford-Colledge.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Wha
<note n="(m)" place="margin">diggs a pit</note> howks a hole for ony other,</l>
               <l>His ſel'
<note n="(n)" place="margin">fall in</note> faw in, were he my Brother.</l>
               <l>Now <hi>Ignoramus</hi>
                  <note n="(o)" place="margin">muſt</note> mun advance,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(p)" place="margin">Among the reſt</note> Amang the laive to take his chance.</l>
               <l>What's ſaid before, to's Charge was layd,</l>
               <l>And other Clarty tricks he play'd.</l>
               <l>It's true he had the common Vogue,</l>
               <l>Yet upon Tryal found a Rogue;</l>
               <l>For all his Lownry was diſcover'd,</l>
               <l>And aw the Pleadings that he offer'd,</l>
               <l>Were over-ruled by the Court;</l>
               <l>And he <hi>adjudg'd</hi> to anſwer for't.</l>
               <l>The Jury found it <hi>Billa-vera,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>Ketch</hi> had Orders t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> prepare a</l>
               <l>Place convenient for the feat;</l>
               <l>And
<note n="(q)" place="margin">knit.</note> kilt him up i'th' open Street.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>If Treaſon's painted Face appear'd not black,</l>
               <l>Ingage not now for thou haſt ſeen its Back.</l>
               <l>Oft had they by Indulgences been cleans'd,</l>
               <l>But yet their Godleſs Lives were never chang'd:</l>
               <l>Their ſtubborn Necks unmanageable ſtill,</l>
               <l>Thô flexible to all but <hi>Charles</hi> his Will.</l>
               <l>Had they not Grace to check their courſe in time?</l>
               <l>No—All their Penance was repuated Crime.</l>
               <l>By violent Force, and unretarded Pace,</l>
               <l>Dart their black Malice 'gainſt the Rays of Grace.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>When Property had
<note n="(r)" place="margin">called to mind,</note> un-bethought her,</l>
               <l>To what a Market they had brought her,</l>
               <l>She put on her conſid'ring Cap,</l>
               <l>Sadly bewailing her Mishap.</l>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:98884:33"/>
               <l>Her Courage now began to fail,</l>
               <l>(She'd got the feek out of her Tail)</l>
               <l>And all her ſoaring hopes were gane;</l>
               <l>Thus to her ſel' ſhe made her
<note n="(ſ)" place="margin">moan.</note> main.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alas! what was in my
<note n="(t)" place="margin">Fooliſh</note> Daft Mind,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thus to my ſel' to preuve unkind?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>When I was well, I could no guide me,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But let the ſtriddling Piper ride me,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And then for cov'ring of my ſhame,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Was fain to yoak wi' ſyke a
<note n="(u)" place="margin">Ignoramus</note> yane.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My
<note n="(x)" place="margin">Portion</note> Tougher geud is ſpent and gane.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>There's nae hail tatter on my Back,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nor am I Dame of ya peur plack.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Beſides I'm famiſh't quite with hunger,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(y)" place="margin">In truth</note> 
                  <hi>Forſeuth I can indure nae langer.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oh—! Wae betide this galloping!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I've got my fill of wallopping!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I ha' na Houſe to put my Head in!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But forc't to ligg upon the
<note n="(z)" place="margin">Dung-hill.</note> Middin!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">My Lady Prerogative's Women,</note> Prudence <hi>and</hi> Patience <hi>will deride me,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And</hi> Juſtice <hi>ſhe will nev'r abide me;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Charity'll <hi>punſh me out o' Dore,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(<hi>For</hi> Grace <hi>and I fell out before.</hi>)</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ay me! how orderly they trip,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Attending on her
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Madam Prerogative!</note> Lady, ſhip!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And was not I a very wiſe one,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To gang and make my ſel' a
<note n="(c)" place="margin">by-Song? or thing to be wondred at?</note> by-zon?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Had I the Office that I had,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I'de nev'r again preuve ha'fe ſae mad.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Hen-wife, Groundleſs-Jealouſie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>(Shame take her) ſhe bewitched me.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Her
<note n="(d)" place="margin">Crutches</note> Stilts ſhe was not able to handle,</l>
               <l>But e'en as woak as ſhe cou'd wandle:</l>
               <l>Upon her Feet ſhe cou'd no keep,</l>
               <l>But there tumbl'd down and fell a ſleep.</l>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:98884:33"/>
               <l>My
<note n="(e)" place="margin">Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative</note> Lady then had juſt walk't out,</l>
               <l>Some ha'fe a mile or thereabout,</l>
               <l>Her Bus'neſs was for to have ſeen</l>
               <l>A Neighbour's Wife, was lying in.</l>
               <l>And with her ſhe took <hi>Charity,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To Chat and bear her Company.</l>
               <l>As
<note n="(f)" place="margin">ſoon</note> ſeun as ev'r ſhe did her ſpy,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My Life,</hi> quo ſhe, <hi>it's</hi> Property.</l>
               <l>O dear! how nimbly they did ſtickle!</l>
               <l>When they perceiv'd her in that pickle,</l>
               <l>For ſhe cou'd neither
<note n="(g)" place="margin">go</note> gang nor ſtand;</l>
               <l>My Lady then lent her a Hand.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My Joe</hi> (quo ſhe) <hi>I need no
<note n="(h)" place="margin">inquire</note> ſpeer</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>What wind it was that blew you here;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>It nev'r was better like to preuve,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Since you teuk on wi' your hang'd leuve.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Why came ye not to your auld Dame?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"Madam, quo ſhe, I e'en thought ſhame.</l>
               <l>"Wa's me that ever I was born,</l>
               <l>"For I'ſe get baith the Skaith and Scorn.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>No</hi> Property, <hi>I's nane of theſe;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tho I can kenn my Friends fra faes.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Come</hi> Charity <hi>let's get her in,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To let her ſtarve were deadly Sin.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hing on the Pan, let Milk be boil'd;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Meat's no' for her, her Stomach's ſpoil'd.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fetch me yon Cordial fra my Cloſet,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Put it to'er Head, and let her doſe it.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>So— give na mair, ſhe'as got her part,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>She's weak, 'twill take her by the Heart.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Poſſet's right, here—take this
<note n="(i)" place="margin">Spoon,</note> Speun,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Drink, ſup it off,—when that is
<note n="(k)" place="margin">done;</note> deun,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ye may lye down and take a Nod,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And reſt your ſel' i'th' name o' God.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>My Lady to the <hi>Ward-robe</hi> hy's,</l>
               <l>Opens a Trunk, and there ſhe ſpy's</l>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:98884:34"/>
               <l>A Milk-white Smock, of dainty Linnin,</l>
               <l>(Indeed it was of her awn Spinning)</l>
               <l>Quoifs, Gorgets, Heuds, Bands, Point <hi>Venee,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As curious wark as yane ſhall ſee.</l>
               <l>Forſeuth ye wou'd ha' thought it Sin,</l>
               <l>To've put a foul Finger therein.</l>
               <l>Upon a Pin hung a Silk Manty,</l>
               <l>And
<note n="(l)" place="margin">Petticoat</note> Wily-Coat (to make her Canty;)</l>
               <l>Sae right and fixt, nathing did lack,</l>
               <l>They nev'r were thrice upon her Back.</l>
               <l>Baith Hoſe and
<note n="(m)" place="margin">Shoes,</note> Sheun, and Gleuv's ſhe ſought,</l>
               <l>Whilk for her proper wear were bought.</l>
               <l>When aw thea things aſide were laid,</l>
               <l>My Lady rapp't—up came her Maid.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Prudence,</hi> quo ſhe, <hi>take my advice,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Firſt clear
<note n="(n)" place="margin">Property</note> you Laſs of Scabs and Lice:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then take that trimming whilk ligs there,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And graith her featly ev'ry where:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And let me never ſee her Face,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Till ſhe be in a
<note n="(o)" place="margin">handſomer</note> deſter caſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>It's now five hours o'th'
<note n="(p)" place="margin">Afternoon,</note> Afternoun,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And time I had my Veſpers
<note n="(q)" place="margin">done.</note> deun.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>When it ſtrikes ſax, then</hi> Grace <hi>may come,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And lead her to the Chappel-Room.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>My Lady's orders were obey'd,</l>
               <l>And aw things deun juſt as ſhe ſaid.</l>
               <l>As ſeun as ev'r ſhe leuk't upon her,</l>
               <l>She
<note n="(r)" place="margin">lowly kneeling,</note> laighly baiking, made her Honour.</l>
               <l>My Lady then a ſmiling fell,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Now ye leuk ſunckat like your ſel'.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Your
<note n="(ſ)" place="margin">very feeble</note> Wankle Leggs canno' ſupport ye,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sae ſit ye down, 'till I exhort ye.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"Madam, indeed it's your geud Nature,</l>
               <l>"That blenks ſae blythly on your Creature.</l>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:98884:34"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tell what's become of thy ſweet Baby?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"I thought it wou'd not pleaſe your Lady</l>
               <l>"ſhip, it look't ſae like its Dady;</l>
               <l>"I have diſown'd it quite for mine,</l>
               <l>"And ſent it o'er to <hi>Caroline;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"To ſhuffle in its Syre's Plantation,</l>
               <l>"And mend the thorough-Reformation.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>What courſe of Life will ye lead now?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"The very ſame beſt pleaſes you.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Troth,</hi> Property, <hi>for mine awn pairt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I'll nev'r keep Miſchief in my Heart.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Here,—take the Keys, and ſtay nae
<note n="(t)" place="margin">longer,</note> langer,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Stir eaſily 'till ye grow
<note n="(u)" place="margin">ſtronger.</note> ſtranger.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And tatling Bablers do not hear,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They'll buzze fond ſtories in your Ear.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The meaneſt Servant of my Train,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shall nev'r ha' reaſon to Complain.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Sir, merrily ſhe
<note n="(x)" place="margin">went</note> gade away,</l>
               <l>And all was made up in dry Hay.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>When Friendly Heav'n 's diſpos'd to ſmile on Kings,</l>
               <l>And Providential Bleſſings prune their Wings</l>
               <l>To viſt us—</l>
               <l>Peace, Plenty's Mother thruſts into the Croud,</l>
               <l>And peaceful Bays to Monarchs Brows allow'd;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Janus</hi> chain'd up, the fierce <hi>Bellona</hi> bow's,</l>
               <l>And ſmooths the Furrows of her wrinkled Brows:</l>
               <l>The Court, a Nurſery of Piety;</l>
               <l>The Bord'ring Nations ſtand amaz'd to ſee</l>
               <l>That Bliſs, and envy the Felicity.</l>
               <l>But oh! the Frenzie of a pop'lar Rage,</l>
               <l>It turns a Golden, to an Iron Age!</l>
               <l>Stung with Rebellion, ſwell'd with Serpent's Pride,</l>
               <l>The Healthful-feeding-Tree it lays aſide;</l>
               <l>And then no Fruit can pleaſe, but what's deny'd.</l>
               <l>It toils for Sorrow, 'till its ſtrength be ſpent,</l>
               <l>And makes the very Sin a Puniſhment.</l>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:98884:35"/>
               <l>O'erwhelm'd at laſt, of all Aſſiſtance void,</l>
               <l>Muſt Plunging ſink, and ſinking be deſtroy'd.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Too raſh my Muſe! what? no Deliverance?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Look up, deſpair not, ſee who does Advance.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Iſaac <hi>is bound, and on the Altar laid,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The healing Angel ſpeaks, the ſtroak is ſtay'd.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>Their Gracious Maſter after that,</l>
               <l>Was far leſs troubled with their Prate:</l>
               <l>Nae thanks to ſome for their geud Will,</l>
               <l>But God's
<note n="(y)" place="margin">above</note> abeun the Devil ſtill.</l>
               <l>Sae lang as Earth was his abode,</l>
               <l>He liv'd and dy'd i'th' fear o' God.</l>
               <l>No doubt his Sins are all forgiv'n,</l>
               <l>And his dear Saul's with God in Heav'n.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>In Heav'n with God, 'tis ſure, Muſe ſing the reſt;</l>
               <l>What can'ſt thou ſay—? fall ſhort,—ſo have the beſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <lg>
               <head>Epitaphium.</head>
               <l>Nor ly's, nor dy's, but fly's the ſoaring <hi>Charles,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whoſe Name's eſteem'd above the richeſt Pearles.</l>
               <l>Fly—? So he muſt, to the Divinity,</l>
               <l>There's room to ſtretch his Soul,—Infinity</l>
               <l>Is ſpacious, that will do't, and no leſs can,</l>
               <l>To him who dy'd a Saint; liv'd more than Man.</l>
               <l>Wou'dſt thou know where this ſacred Relict lyes?</l>
               <l>Kneel,—kiſs this Urn,—now dry thy dropping Eyes.</l>
            </lg>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>Oh! <hi>Landlord</hi> ye ha' made me ſory!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land,</speaker>
               <l>No doubt, yet I've a healing ſtory,</l>
               <l>I'll tell it as we home-ward ride.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>Geud Sir, I can no' langer bide.</l>
               <l>I pray you tell it me juſt now?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>I'll do't then to make ſtraight with you.</l>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:98884:35"/>
               <l>Lay by your
<note n="(z)" place="margin">Tobacco</note> Pipe, in ſilence ſit you ſtill,</l>
               <l>And Interrupt me not.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">No more</note> Nae mair I will.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">Coronation day.</note> This Morning early as I ſlumb'ring lay,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aurora</hi> handing in the welcome Day,</l>
               <l>A Glorious Youth appear'd (me-thought) and ſaid,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Come follow me, refuſe that flatt'ring bed.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His ami'able Countenance my Lodgings grac't,</l>
               <l>I rowz'd my ſelf, and his ſafe Footſteps trac't.</l>
               <l>When feeble I fell faint in Travelling,</l>
               <l>He mounted me upon his Silver Wing.</l>
               <l>He ſtream'd me to the New <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>There gently, gently ſet me down by him.</l>
               <l>The Splendour of that place ſurmounts my Tongue,</l>
               <l>Melodiouſly was <hi>Elohim</hi>'s Praiſes ſung.</l>
               <l>The Beaming Rays of that Celeſtial Sun,</l>
               <l>Compell'd my yielding Eyes the Light to ſhun.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I am thine Angel-Guardian,</hi> he did ſay,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I'll ſhew thee what is done in Heav'n this day:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Come, liſt'n with Rev'rence, but no more preſume;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then o'er my Face he lay'd his downy Plume.</l>
               <l>I heard the voice of dreadful Majeſty,</l>
               <l>But wonderful! it did not terrifie!</l>
               <l>Majeſtick—Mildneſs—do not yet aſpire,</l>
               <l>Our God <hi>Jehovah</hi>'s a conſuming Fire.</l>
               <l>Then Palpitation ſeiz'd my trembling heart,</l>
               <l>My palſi'd hands did quake, and ev'ry part;</l>
               <l>My ſhiv'ring Joints could not their burthens Bear.</l>
               <l>At which, my tender Tutor, <hi>do not fear,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But be you humble, and be chearful here.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And thus th' Eternal Father to his Son,</l>
               <l>And to his Holy Spirit, "<hi>We are One;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"Before time was, we were, when time began,</l>
               <l>"'Mongſt other Beings we created Man,</l>
               <l>"And all things elſe, which can in place be ſeen;</l>
               <l>"But now this day let us make King and Queen.</l>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:98884:36"/>
               <l>"I'll give them Wiſdom, Wiſdom to Create</l>
               <l>"Affection, and call home alienate;</l>
               <l>"My ſecret Counſels I'll to them unfold;</l>
               <l>"Juſtice and Mercy ſhall their Throne uphold,</l>
               <l>The Everlaſting Truth gave his Conſent,</l>
               <l>Saying—"Eternal Father, my Content</l>
               <l>"Has always been your bleſſed Will to do,</l>
               <l>"And to Compleat them I'll contribute too.</l>
               <l>"I'll give them true Obedience to our Law,</l>
               <l>"Their Inclinations to our Precepts draw;</l>
               <l>"My precious Blood ſhall not in vain be ſpilt,</l>
               <l>"It's balming Vertues ſhall by them be felt:</l>
               <l>"Their Burthen's heavy, I will make them ſtrong;</l>
               <l>"Alleviate the Croſs they've carry'd long.</l>
               <l>The enliv'ning Dove expans't his hov'ring Wing,</l>
               <l>So he—"I will deſcend upon my King,</l>
               <l>"And Queen.—</l>
               <l>"I'll breeze a gentle Gale into their Mouths,</l>
               <l>"They ſhall both practice, and defend my Truths.</l>
               <l>"Two Cloven Tongues within their Lips I'll place;</l>
               <l>"And them repleniſh with my ſeven-fold-Grace.</l>
               <l>This is no task, O God, but eaſe to you,</l>
               <l>For what cannot Omnipotency do?</l>
               <l>Amen to all—<hi>Iſaias</hi> did advance;</l>
               <l>A Prophet fam'd for matchleſs Elegance:</l>
               <l>He warbl'd out with towring Trumpet ſound,</l>
               <l>Take right his Theme—<hi>Here's only to be found,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Object of all ſupernat'ral Bliſs,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who was from the beginning, who ſtill is,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And ſhall be after mould'ring time is paſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ev'n</hi> Alpha <hi>and</hi> Omega, <hi>firſt and laſt.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>It was not for himſelf he did Create,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>There can be no Addition to Compleat.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He gave us being that we might be Bleſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And banquetted at this nev'r ending feaſt;</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:98884:36"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>And as his Power Divine has not dimenſion,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Our Virtues are not ſuch but by Extenſion.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As happy Souls come fleeting to this place,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Our accidental Glory will increaſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Therefore let us Communicate our ſtore,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The more we give, we ſtill enjoy the more.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We'll ſend ſome tokens to</hi> Great Britains <hi>King,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And Queen, let's make a free-will Offering.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>They all Conſent and <hi>Allelujah</hi> Sing.</l>
               <l>Receptacles thoſe propines to receive,</l>
               <l>Are brought, of whom I knew, thus each one gave.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Virgin-Mother</hi> bleſt 'mong Women kind,</l>
               <l>Made the firſt Offer ſuited to their mind.</l>
               <l>"To them I'll give my rare Humility,</l>
               <l>"Temper'd with Pow'r and lofty Majeſty:</l>
               <l>"They ſhall conteſt Heav'n's Pleaſure to fulfil,</l>
               <l>"Saying—<hi>Be't to your ſervants as ye will.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Three Hierarchys of Angels, Orders nine,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Seraphims</hi> inflam'd with Love divine,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Cherubims</hi> with Sciences repleat,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Refulgent Thrones</hi> are the Almighty's Seat.</l>
               <l>The <hi>ſhining Virtues, Ruling Dominations,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Powers</hi> exult, with joyful Acclamations,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Principalitys</hi> their Tryumphs ſing:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Arch-Angels</hi> always ready miniſtring,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Angels</hi> ſtill for Ambaſſy's prepar'd,</l>
               <l>And all of them, their Gifts with freedom ſhar'd.</l>
               <l>Saint <hi>Michael</hi>—"I will buckle to his ſide</l>
               <l>"This brandiſh't Blade, which tam'd the Prince of Pride;</l>
               <l>"And there ſhall none be able to Contend,</l>
               <l>"<hi>With</hi> James <hi>and</hi> Mary, <hi>whom I will defend.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Saint <hi>Raphael</hi>—"<hi>I</hi> did take him by the Hand,</l>
               <l>"Conducting him to that thrice happy Land,</l>
               <l>"From whence the choiceſt Comforts of his Life,</l>
               <l>"<hi>Rich-Virtue, Honour, Beauty in a Wife.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:98884:37"/>
               <l>"Neither did I forſake them in Exile,</l>
               <l>"(For ſo it was) but car'fully that while,</l>
               <l>"I pointed out ſafe Footings in their way,</l>
               <l>"I foil'd the wicked Sp'rit which ſought to ſlay;</l>
               <l>"And ſhade the Light of <hi>Britains</hi> beaming Day.</l>
               <l>"Nor is mine Office out, I'll ſtill take pains,</l>
               <l>"<hi>Adjutor to their Angels Guardians.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Enoch</hi>—"They ſhall in Contemplation ſtay,</l>
               <l>"And with their God walk hand in hand all day;</l>
               <l>"Yea, when tranſlated to this happy ſtate,</l>
               <l>"My ſelf ſhall welcome them at Heav'ns gate.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jacob</hi>—"Come reſt your Heads upon my ſtone:</l>
               <l>"Your Toil is paſt, your anxious Hours are gone.</l>
               <l>"By the Seditious never ſhall be forgot,</l>
               <l>"<hi>That God was in this Place, we knew it not.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi>—"Here take my Meekneſs with my Rod,</l>
               <l>"Dark <hi>Aegypt</hi> (where his People ſought abode)</l>
               <l>"Shall be contemn'd, here's <hi>Canaans</hi> Property,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Not Slaves to Rebells, free Men</hi> James <hi>to thee.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Joſhua</hi>—"Let me add Conduct to their Arms,</l>
               <l>"Whoſe Warlike Captains, with their Marſhal Charms,</l>
               <l>"Shall guide their Troops throughout their promis't Land,</l>
               <l>"<hi>Nor Foreign, nor Home-Foes ſhall them withſtand.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>David</hi>—"Go on, chant out th' inceſſant praiſe</l>
               <l>"Of your Redemption in Angelick Lays:</l>
               <l>"My well-tun'd Harp, ſhall with your Hearts agree,</l>
               <l>"Not two, but one continu'd Harmony.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Daniel</hi>—"Sharp Quickneſs to his Councils Eyes,</l>
               <l>"They ſhall unriddle hidden Myſteries</l>
               <l>"Of State; the Judges ſhall expound the Law,</l>
               <l>"And all Diſſenters to Allegiance draw.</l>
               <l>Conſtant-Couragious-Proto-Martyr-<hi>Stephen,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>—"My Blood for <hi>Jeſus</hi>'s ſake was freely given,</l>
               <l>"The Frantick Rout againſt me did conſpire,</l>
               <l>"The more they threw me down, I bounc't the higher:</l>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:98884:37"/>
               <l>"Did they not ſeek to ſtop this Royal Breath?</l>
               <l>"And by the Rabble were ſton'd to worſe than Death.</l>
               <l>"But ſtrong-built Virtue cannot eas'ly fall,</l>
               <l>"Their Patience, Conquering Patience Conquer'd all;</l>
               <l>"They Patient droop't, now they to Glory riſe;</l>
               <l>"Their Prayer—<hi>O Lord forgive our Enemys.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Saint <hi>Paul</hi>—"The Sword ſhall not be giv'n in vain,</l>
               <l>"But for their own, and all their Subjects gain;</l>
               <l>"The haggard-Vaſſal ſhall obey his Prince,</l>
               <l>"<hi>Not out of Slaviſh Fear, but Conſcience.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Saints <hi>Ambroſe, Jerome, painful Auguſtine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With more, who did the Churches Light refine;</l>
               <l>"—Their Cautious Prelats ſhall in Vnitie,</l>
               <l>"Maintain the Cath'lick Faith; that Faith which we</l>
               <l>"Undauntedly aſſerted ev'n to Wonder,</l>
               <l>"Not tear the ſeamleſs Coat of Chriſt aſunder.</l>
               <l>"That Faith whereon the Factious take no hold,</l>
               <l>"<hi>As but one Shepherd, ſo but one Sheepfold:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"Flat Sence, and flagging Reaſon ſink beneath</l>
               <l>"Stupendious Miſt'rys of a Chriſtian's Faith.</l>
               <l>Saint <hi>George,</hi> "They've honor'd me, I'll honor them.</l>
               <l>"Upon Saint <hi>George</hi>'s-day Saint <hi>George</hi> will climb:</l>
               <l>"Saint <hi>George</hi> for <hi>England</hi>—Now they well may ſay,</l>
               <l>"<hi>Let's go to prayers, this is Saint</hi> George<hi>'s-day.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Saint <hi>Andrew</hi>—"For their guard I'll rear my Croſs,</l>
               <l>"The <hi>Thiſtles</hi> goodneſs they ſhall all ingroſs:</l>
               <l>"<hi>Red-Lion-Rampant from his den ſhall roar</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"<hi>In their defence, as he as done oft before.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Saint <hi>Patrick</hi>—"With my Lyre I'll tame their Foes,</l>
               <l>"The ſtouteſt Rebel <hi>Thraſo</hi> ſha'n't oppoſe,</l>
               <l>"Their ſpotleſs White ſhall nev'r ſuſtain a Wrong</l>
               <l>"From chatt'ring <hi>Magpye,</hi> nor <hi>invenom'd Tongue.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Laſt, weeping <hi>Rachel,</hi> with her Fountain Eyes,</l>
               <l>Laid in an Handkerchief wherewith ſhe dry's</l>
               <l>Her blubb'ry Cheeks—"Give this to Widow-Queen,</l>
               <l>"She ſhall have Joys for Sorrows ſhe has ſeen.</l>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:98884:38"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Arch-Angel Gabriel</hi> b'ing Elect Envoy,</l>
               <l>To ambaſs down Congrat'latory Joy,</l>
               <l>Hoiſts up his Feather-Sails, and veers about;</l>
               <l>Then in the Airy-Ocean lanches out.</l>
               <l>Flight time's out done, ha'fe ſecond is not o're,</l>
               <l>E're this ſame Agile Spirit ſpoke before</l>
               <l>Our Royal Pair—<hi>Some preſents here I bring,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They're Heav'nly Preſents, from a Heav'nly King,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And Heav'nly Subjects, to adorn your Throne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They'll gild your names when ruſty age is gone.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This ſubtile Eſſence wheels about, and flys,</l>
               <l>His Pinnion-Oars divide the azure Skys,</l>
               <l>And drowzie <hi>Somnus</hi> here unſeal'd mine eyes.</l>
               <l>I rowz'd, I roſe, I dreſt, to Pray'rs withdrew;</l>
               <l>Imploring Heav'n my Viſion might prove true.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>I doubt it not
<note n="(a)" place="margin">ſince</note> ſen their ways pleaſe the Lord,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Grace, Peace</hi> and <hi>Plenty</hi> he'l to them afford.</l>
               <l>I dream'd a Dream a while ago,</l>
               <l>But with it I'll not trouble you.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>I prethee tell't, if't be no Hurt?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>The worſt, Sir, is but harmleſs Sport.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(z)" place="margin">One Night</note> Ya Night I went to Bed right late,</l>
               <l>A hundred Maggots in my Pate,</l>
               <l>I dream'd at my Bed's ſide did ſtand,</l>
               <l>A Jeſuit; and in his Hand,</l>
               <l>A Conſecrated Gun (God bleſs me!)</l>
               <l>He cou'd no' fix't, and ſae he miſs't me.</l>
               <l>Then out drew he a Gully-knife.</l>
               <l>With that he
<note n="(a)" place="margin">parted</note> twinn'd me and my Life.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">inſtantly</note> Off hand I ran into the Town,</l>
               <l>Stark dead I rally'd up and down;</l>
               <l>I
<note n="(c)" place="margin">like a Calf</note> blair'd and
<note n="(d)" place="margin">how I'd like a Dog when he is hurt.</note> whindg'd lyke ony man,</l>
               <l>And down my Cheeks the ſalt Tears ran;</l>
               <l>I ſhouted out—Oh—! Waes is me</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I've loſt my Head, dear Friends ye ſee.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:98884:38"/>
               <l>I durſt ha' wager'd a gray Groat,</l>
               <l>The very Blade ſtack croſs my Throat.</l>
               <l>Albeit I found my fel' beguil'd,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(e)" place="margin">Moſt</note> Maiſt o' the Towns-men juſt ran wild.</l>
               <l>Tho this was but Fantaſtick Wound,</l>
               <l>There's not a few fell in a Swound.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>You thought but ſo, it was their Quackery.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>De'il fetch't, was it but
<note n="(f)" place="margin">Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand-dealing.</note> Jewkry-pawkry?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>Goſſip, I think you'l not deny,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tony</hi> had finger in that Pye?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>Ay Sir, as ſure as I'ſe alive,</l>
               <l>For e'en as e'er I hope to thrive,</l>
               <l>There's very few that ev'r
<note n="(g)" place="margin">meddl'd</note> meddl'd with him;</l>
               <l>But firſt or laſt he did undo them.</l>
               <l>I'll tell ye what a Trick he play'd me,</l>
               <l>And fain wou'd
<note n="(h)" place="margin">a nimble-Tongu'd Claw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</note> Gobby here deceiv'd me;</l>
               <l>But, Sir, I got him at the Catch,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tony</hi> has yance met with his Match.</l>
               <l>I felt his Pulſe, and Pocket too,</l>
               <l>And then, Quod I, <hi>Tony adieu.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This Swindger at Saint <hi>Barthol</hi>'s Fair,</l>
               <l>Where aw the Nimmers do repair:</l>
               <l>(And this was he, without ſuppoſe,</l>
               <l>Or els 'twas Satan in his Cloaths.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(i)" place="margin">Betwixt</note> Amell them twa was ſike a League,</l>
               <l>For driving on a damn'd Intreague;</l>
               <l>The t'one the t'other had ſae haunted,</l>
               <l>To knaw which, which, muſt be acquainted.)</l>
               <l>He jogg'd me gently on the Elbow,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Come here geud Fellow, ſee what I'll do:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"You
<note n="(k)" place="margin">look</note> leuk not like a <hi>Tory-Scot,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"On you I will beſtow a Pot;</l>
               <l>He had a thing under his Coat,</l>
               <l>Juſt like a Fiddle as I thought.</l>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:98884:39"/>
               <l>Quo—he, <hi>I've Travell'd far and near,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And this has wone me muckle geer;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He
<note n="(l)" place="margin">whiſpers</note> rownds me ſoftly in the Ear,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Take my gend Counſel, do not fear.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My Bird, here is for to be ſeen,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>What thou ne'er ſaw wi' thy
<note n="(m)" place="margin">two eyes.</note> two een.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dear
<note n="(n)" place="margin">honey-love,</note> hinny-Leuve, ye little knaw,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But go, I underſtand the Law:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I'll draw a Compaſs and nae mair,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Twixt it and Treaſon but a hair.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tony,</hi> ſaid I, ye chance may trip,</l>
               <l>"Where were ye if your Thumb ſhou'd ſlip?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I fear not</hi> (crafty <hi>Tony</hi> adds)</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Our doughty</hi> Ignoramus <hi>Ladds</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Can play at</hi> Iriſh, <hi>their Back-game</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Will ſave baith</hi> Tony, <hi>and his fame:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Damnation they will make their Lot,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>E're Idol</hi>-Tony <hi>gang to th' Pot.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>When that's deun I's nought in their debt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My hazard makes an equal ſet.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But Leuvie, here's a Courteſte,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which out o' kindneſs I'll do thee:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The</hi> Torys <hi>now thou ſee'ſt are undone,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(o)" place="margin">Next</note> 
                  <hi>Neiſt year thou ſhall be Mayor of</hi> London;</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(p)" place="margin">Liberatores patriae.</note> 
                  <hi>Thy name Ingrav'n upon a Pillar,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Here—ſee my Lad, and keep thy Siller.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He lay'd his Trinckums on the Table,</l>
               <l>Whilk I'll deſcribe as I am able:</l>
               <l>But leſt there ſhou'd be ſome miſtack,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Here—Boy, bring me a bit o'
<note n="(q)" place="margin">Chalk.</note> Cauck.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(r)" place="margin">This kind of ſhow I have ſeen in <hi>Holland,</hi> and in <hi>England</hi> at Fairs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> I think it was near
<note n="(ſ)" place="margin">two</note> tw a Foot lang;</l>
               <l>Or there about, (I'll do nae wrang.)</l>
               <l>This end was juſt twa inches o're,</l>
               <l>And that was ſax, and
<note n="(t)" place="margin">little bit</note> bittock more.</l>
               <l>A piece of Criſtal here put on,</l>
               <l>The
<note n="(u)" place="margin">biggneſs</note> muckledeum of ha'fe a Crown.</l>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:98884:39"/>
               <l>He had a Frame of narrow Glaſs,</l>
               <l>I judge three Foot of length it was.</l>
               <l>With Pictures Painted here and there,</l>
               <l>You'll ſee the uſe on't, what ſhou'd mair.</l>
               <l>That far end wide, this near end ſtrait</l>
               <l>Did magnifie at a huge rate.</l>
               <l>A twinkling light ſet at the back,</l>
               <l>In little
<note n="(x)" place="margin">Lanthorn</note> Bowet—Wyly quack.</l>
               <l>And there's the
<note n="(y)" place="margin">right way of any thing.</note> geeg of his <hi>Jimcrack.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He bids me ſet this Eye apart,</l>
               <l>(Ha'fe ſight is beſt for Jugler's Art)</l>
               <l>And thus ask't I, ſae he reply'd,</l>
               <l>Tho I dare Swear he often ly'd.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>What Worthy Men are hither ſent?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"A true proteſting Parliament,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>(I'll ſhift it to another pin)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>What's this?</hi> "It's Pop'ry coming in.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And wha is you Trav'lling fra home?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"Our Clergy Gallopping to <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>O! Wonderful! <hi>And what is there?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"<hi>French</hi> Navies Sailing in the Air.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And what's that in you darksome ſpot.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"Baith Queen and Duke in Papiſt Plot.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>What then is this whilk end ways follow's?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"Black-bills and Pilgrims, haly Gully's.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wha's you of Sundry
<note n="(z)" place="margin">Shapes</note> Macks and Faſhions?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"A Doctor ſaving thea three Nations.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>What Siller's you to pay the Coſt?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"Seaven hundred pound he Swears he loſt.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>This Raree-ſhew</hi> I <hi>prethee tell?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Sir <hi>E.B.G.</hi>
                  </note> A dead Man riding by his ſel'.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>What now—I vow I canno' gueſs?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"The <hi>Obſervator</hi> hearing Maſs.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Again—I ſpeer'd what I eſpy'd?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"Aw the hail Court be popify'd.</l>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:98884:40"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>What garr's thea
<note n="(b)" place="margin">dol'ful</note> deulfow folke complain?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"My Bairn, their Property is gane,</l>
               <l>"They hourly leuk they ſhou'd be ſlain.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>What's this?</hi> "It's an Excluſion-Bill,</l>
               <l>"Leſt Monarchy ſhou'd happen ill.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>What can this be
<note n="(c)" place="margin">which looks o oddly?</note> whilk leuks ſae oddly?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"Hey—geer enough for aw the Godly.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>What's ligging in that little hole?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"The King's advantage by the Pole.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wha's here telling him idle Storys?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"Nane—make him peur, and he'll be Glorious.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O wally</hi> Tony! <hi>what is that?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"A Black-Box cramm'd wi' God knows what.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>What are thea Writings cloſely Seal'd up?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"The ſame were found in <hi>Celiers</hi> Meal-Tub.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>What wonder's this, ſpeak if ye pleaſe?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"It is the Meun made of Green-Cheeſe.</l>
               <l>This is the laſt, <hi>What ſee I now?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"A Hundred men to Swear all's true.</l>
               <l>He drank to me the t'other Cup,</l>
               <l>And thus again he wheadl'd me up.</l>
               <l>"And now, dear
<note n="(d)" place="margin">Brother</note> Billy, this is right,</l>
               <l>"Sae do no' ſit in your awn light.</l>
               <l>"I knaw ye are a man of Reaſon,</l>
               <l>"And this ye'll find the fitteſt Seaſon;</l>
               <l>"Strike in as if ſome Friend o' mine,</l>
               <l>"Make up your Hay while Sun do's ſhine;</l>
               <l>"And here's my Hand (what ev'r ſhall chance,)</l>
               <l>"Ye ſhall no' miſs my furtherance.</l>
               <l>"This thing I wou'd not undertake,</l>
               <l>"But only for my
<note n="(e)" place="margin">Country's ſake.</note> Keuntry's ſake.</l>
               <l>"For I had rather live at eaſe,</l>
               <l>"With ha'ſe a
<note n="(f)" place="margin">a thick Cake bak't be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Fire.</note> Bannock made of Peaſe,</l>
               <l>"Stinking Butter and Rotten Cheeſe,</l>
               <l>"Ev'n <hi>Sl—by Be—ls</hi> dayly-meſs.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:98884:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>"Cauſe up and down I
<note n="(f)" place="margin">am not able</note> dow no' ride,</l>
               <l>"As I ha' done— <hi>Alas my ſide.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"You hear of this Damn'd Papiſh-Plot?</l>
               <l>"Nae honeſt man can ſave his Throat!</l>
               <l>"See what a pitch the Doctor's run to,</l>
               <l>"What high Preferment he has come to!</l>
               <l>"If things (we doubt 'em not) ſhou'd hit,</l>
               <l>"Ere long ye'll ſee him higher yet.</l>
               <l>"My Dow, rub up thy Memory,</l>
               <l>"For thou knaws e'en as well as he.</l>
               <l>"Be careful Birdy, caſt about,</l>
               <l>"Speak firſt, and I will help thee out.</l>
               <l>"Ay—Right—think on't, and then begin,</l>
               <l>"Thou'lt be a Credit to thy kin.</l>
               <l>"Or if this time ye canno' ſtay,</l>
               <l>"Come to my Houſe ſome other day,</l>
               <l>"I'll pay the
<note n="(g)" place="margin">Reck'ning</note> Lawing—gang your way.</l>
               <l>"But hark ye me, I ſhou'd ha' ſpoken</l>
               <l>"Another thing I had forgotten;</l>
               <l>"Tho I've but ſeldom ſeen that Face,</l>
               <l>"Yet in thy very look there's Grace:</l>
               <l>"This kindneſs I'll do you—In caſe</l>
               <l>"Ye be ought Straitned in your Purſe,</l>
               <l>"And canno' get you Arms and Horſe;</l>
               <l>"Tell me your mind if ye be ſcant?</l>
               <l>"Great pity ſike as ye ſhou'd want.</l>
               <l>"Or afterward I'll ſend my Man,</l>
               <l>"To meet you at the <hi>Amſterdam;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"But whatſoever ſhou'd
<note n="(h)" place="margin">befall</note> befaw,</l>
               <l>"Take this—for to be doing with
<note n="(i)" place="margin">all.</note> aw.</l>
               <l>"Here—ſet thine hand to this
<note n="(k)" place="margin">A Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive or a few Depoſitions only.</note> bit Writing,</l>
               <l>"And ſwear it is thine awn Inditing.</l>
               <l>"And Sweety, if thou'lt but obey,</l>
               <l>"Thou'lt reap the Fruit another day,</l>
               <l>"When thy Friend <hi>Tony</hi>'s
<note n="(l)" place="margin">cloath'd</note> clad in Clay.</l>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:98884:41"/>
               <l>"We've <hi>Engliſh</hi> Evidence
<note n="(m)" place="margin">enough,</note> enow,</l>
               <l>"And of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> not a few;</l>
               <l>"Laſt <hi>Sunday</hi> we drew in a Jew,</l>
               <l>"And fain wou'd had a <hi>Scotch-man</hi> too;</l>
               <l>"But ne'er had that geud Luck till now.</l>
               <l>Thought I, what 'vengeance can he mean,</l>
               <l>The like of this was never ſeen!</l>
               <l>Some Miſchief ſurely he intends,</l>
               <l>Of me he nev'r ſhall brook his ends;</l>
               <l>(But yet the
<note n="(n)" place="margin">Silver</note> Siller made ſome mends.)</l>
               <l>"As ſlyly as thy
<note n="*" place="margin">falſe</note> faus Chafts waggs,</l>
               <l>"The De'il be in thy rotten Baggs,</l>
               <l>"If ever <hi>Andro</hi> here ingage.</l>
               <l>(When Foxes preach
<note n="(o)" place="margin">take heed to</note> tent weel your Geeſe;</l>
               <l>The Lord ſend me to live in Peace.)</l>
               <l>"My Banes oft broken for my King,</l>
               <l>"And thou garr me in Hemp-ſtring ſwing!</l>
               <l>"Gang ſeek your
<note n="(p)" place="margin">looſe fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows</note> Callands with a ſhame,</l>
               <l>"For <hi>Andro</hi> he is nane of them.</l>
               <l>God help't me out my ſel' to ſave,</l>
               <l>And freed me fra that
<note n="(q)" place="margin">flattering</note> fleetching Knave.</l>
               <l>Sir, gin ye thought it but beſtow'd,</l>
               <l>A Sang o' yours were e'en worth
<note n="(r)" place="margin">Gold.</note> Gowd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <opener>
                     <hi>To the Tune of,</hi> Now, now the Fight's done, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </opener>
                  <lg>
                     <head>I</head>
                     <l>Now, now the Feat's done,</l>
                     <l>And the Great <hi>Machiavels,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Lye ſculking in the dark;</l>
                     <l>And they chafe in their Cells:</l>
                     <l>When Loyalty laught,</l>
                     <l>They ſtretch't for the Cauſe,</l>
                     <l>Contriving, Sham-Plotting,</l>
                     <l>To Counter the Laws,</l>
                     <l>They rode on Rebellion;</l>
                     <l>And Royalty bang'd,</l>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:98884:41"/>
                     <l>And their Pupils for Treaſon</l>
                     <l>On Gallow-Tree hang'd.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>II.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Jack Presbyter</hi> ſmil'd,</l>
                     <l>Having fixed his Dart,</l>
                     <l>And wing'd it to 'hit</l>
                     <l>The Great Prince in the Heart:</l>
                     <l>Who calmly withdrew</l>
                     <l>At his Sov'raign's Command,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe Pleaſure, full Meaſure,</l>
                     <l>He ne'er did gainſtand;</l>
                     <l>Now his Foes are diſperſed,</l>
                     <l>And fall'n in diſgrace,</l>
                     <l>Our Paſſion recoil,</l>
                     <l>And give Reaſon it's place.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <head>III.</head>
                     <l>Truth, Truth is the cry,</l>
                     <l>Truth and Juſtice go round,</l>
                     <l>Whilſt Plotters, and Traitors,</l>
                     <l>Lye ſprauling o'th' Ground.</l>
                     <l>Their Cabals are Confounded,</l>
                     <l>Their Evidence flinches,</l>
                     <l>And packing of Parliaments,</l>
                     <l>Throw'n off the Hindges:</l>
                     <l>They'll Rally no more,</l>
                     <l>For an <hi>Oliver</hi> Noſe,</l>
                     <l>Nor Muſter freſh Forces,</l>
                     <l>But flat in the Cloſe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>Well ſaid Sir, I wou'd give a Cow,</l>
               <l>Why I cou'd ſing as well as you.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>But hark ye Friend, one told to me</l>
               <l>A while ago ye were at Sea.</l>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:98884:42"/>
               <l>I like not Plow-ſtilt Math'mat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ans,</l>
               <l>Nor <hi>London</hi> Prentice Politicians;</l>
               <l>Neither care I for Women-Preachers,</l>
               <l>Nor Leather-Apron'd-Goſpel-Teachers,</l>
               <l>Nor any he that wears a Gown,</l>
               <l>Who cants in Country, or in Town,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sedition up, and Pop'ry down.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Let ev'ry Prudent man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>arge,</l>
               <l>What Office falls within his verge.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>I nev'r can tell ye that for ſhame,</l>
               <l>For I am ſure ye will me blame.</l>
               <l>But what care I?
<note n="(ſ)" place="margin">reproof</note> Repren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4+ letters">
                     <desc>••••…</desc>
                  </gap> you</l>
               <l>I well may bear,
<note n="(t)" place="margin">ſince</note> ſen it's my due.</l>
               <l>Now let me ſee,—It is about</l>
               <l>Seaven, or
<note n="(u)" place="margin">eight</note> aught year ſen that fell out.</l>
               <l>Upon our Voyage we were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>The Wind blew fair, to Sea we went.</l>
               <l>Our Skipper wiſe, our Veſſel ſound,</l>
               <l>And to <hi>Weſt India</hi>'s we were bound.</l>
               <l>I learn't ſome Terms in that Tranſaction,</l>
               <l>But fumbl'd baſely when in Action:</l>
               <l>Yet thought my ſelf as skilful as</l>
               <l>The wiſeſt he on Ship-board was.</l>
               <l>Say'd to the Steers-man—<hi>Friend, in caſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ye be ought tyr'd give me your place.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Quoth he, I think ye are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Here,—take my room with aw my Heart.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Here's no particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon meant un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter but the common Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in general, who love to meddle where they have nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Judgment nor Buſineſs.</note> Nay then, thought I, there's muckle doubt</l>
               <l>Can I no' twirrle that ſtick about?</l>
               <l>I had no' deun the Office lang,</l>
               <l>But preſently I ſet aw wrang.</l>
               <l>When they cry'd <hi>Helm a lee,</hi> I ſwear</l>
               <l>I wiſt nae mair nor my blind
<note n="(x)" place="margin">Mare</note> Mier.</l>
               <l>All hands aloft, and ev'ry where,</l>
               <l>The Maiſters Mate Mad as <hi>March</hi>-hare,</l>
               <l>For only ſhift that cou'd be found,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad like to've run the Ship a-ground.</l>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:98884:42"/>
               <l>When Horſes in the Fields lye dying,</l>
               <l>The Carrion
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Crows</note> Craws about them flying</l>
               <l>Will keep a
<note n="(b)" place="margin">croaking,</note> craiking, and I've ſeen,</l>
               <l>Ere they've been dead, their very een</l>
               <l>Pyk't out, and Dogs ha' ſnaſht their Haunches,</l>
               <l>Ay, ſometimes riv'n out aw their Paunches.</l>
               <l>Syklike there was a Rav'nous Tribe,</l>
               <l>(The De'il has not their
<note n="(c)" place="margin">equals</note> maiks beſide)</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(d)" place="margin">Stood</note> Steud on the Shoar to ſee us ſink,</l>
               <l>And Fiſh-way in the Ocean drink.</l>
               <l>Amang the
<note n="(e)" place="margin">reſt</note> laive I did eſpy,</l>
               <l>A Doctor of Divinity,</l>
               <l>Or elſe he ſlants confoundedly.</l>
               <l>But yet ſuppoſe he leuv'd to fib,</l>
               <l>And ſome for that, his Luggs ſhould
<note n="(f)" place="margin">geld:</note> libb:</l>
               <l>Or teach him aumbling by the hand,</l>
               <l>Till he his paces underſtand;</l>
               <l>Or twine a widdy 'bout his
<note n="(g)" place="margin">Neck,</note> Craig,</l>
               <l>To ken him for a ſtraying Naig;</l>
               <l>It's nae ſike wide Compariſon,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For Horſe and Doctor, all is one.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Conjoin for better or for worſe,</l>
               <l>It's Doctor <hi>Oats</hi> makes Doctor Horſe.</l>
               <l>Theſe Queſtions ne'er ſhall trouble me,</l>
               <l>For now he'as tane his right Degree.</l>
               <l>Or if he draw behind the Cart,</l>
               <l>Let it be ſae with aw my Heart;</l>
               <l>If he draw right on any ſcore,</l>
               <l>It's mair nor ev'r he did before.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>This Ship,</hi> quoth he, <hi>we underſtand,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Is fraught wi' Dean and Chapter Land,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rich fat Livings, Biſhops Mannors,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pilgrims, Court and Kirk-Trepanners.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Black-Bills, and</hi> Iriſh, <hi>Tory</hi> Scots,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They're not a Hairs breadth fra our Throats.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:98884:43"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>My ſel' has been
<note n="(h)" place="margin">Salamanca, if you'll truſt him.</note> in other Nations,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Where I ha' ſtudy'd Conjurations,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I'll drive a Storm, the Seas I'le trouble,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And they ſhall find their Danger double;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I'll force the Winds (for I ha' Skill,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To raiſe Auld Nick, lay him wha will.)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>From whence, I hope, when ſhe is loſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>She will be wreck't upon our Coaſt.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If ony claim be made, I'll ſwear</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That we ſaw nought but Papiſh Gear.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Why ſhould we keep it to our loſs?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We burnt it all at</hi> Charing-Croſs.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And for the
<note n="(i)" place="margin">Sir W. W.</note> Guineys and what elſ,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Them we'll divide amang our ſel's.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Doctor having giv'n the Word,</l>
               <l>A Daughty Captain drew his Sword,</l>
               <l>And Vows—<hi>By all my Valiant Deeds,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I will not leave thee in the Weeds.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I'll ſtick to thee as cloſe as</hi> Curtis</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>(Wha will take Care that nane ſhall hurt us)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Till he that buckl'd us ſhall part us.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then end-ways ruſh't another Crew,</l>
               <l>(I canno' tell how many now)</l>
               <l>They ſhouted—<hi>Leaders never ſledge,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For we'll ſtick to you back and edge:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We'll ſwear aw that and meikle mair,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Provided always we have ſhare.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We'll ſwear, and never tire of ſwearing,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And ſwear 'till ſome have loſt their hearing.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Swear in, ſwear out, ſwear off, ſwear on,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And ſwear when Swearing time is gone.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We'll ſwear, and lye, and things ſae handle;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That ſwearing truth ſhall give a ſcandal.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ah! inſtantly a Gale did blow,</l>
               <l>The Seas ran tumbling to and fro:</l>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:98884:43"/>
               <l>Our Skipper ſtep't upon the Hatch,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My Lads,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>let us diſpatch,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And reef the Top-ſail, for I gueſs,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>This Gale is likely to increaſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>What—? mair and mair, our Top-ſail muſt</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Be handed, let no time be loſt.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And our three Low-ſails will not do,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Therefore let's hand our Fores-ſail too.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I think with Main-ſail we'll make ſhift,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sa lang's we have enough of drift.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>This way again, brave Lads make hie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And lay'r in Miſne ballaſt by:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Still worſe and worſe—! Lads here again,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And reef the main-ſail; I ſee plain</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That we ſhall have a dreadfow ſtorm,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pray God our Veſſel take nae harm.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oh! wonderful! the Seas ſtill ſwell,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sure this
<note n="(k)" place="margin">muſt</note> mun be the fiend of Hell!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Our Ship is now ſae toſs't and hurl'd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Our Main-ſail muſt lik'ways be furl'd.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>All will not do,—Plumb—Here's a Road;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caſt Anchor, wait the Will of God.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Some Service preſently provide,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To ſave our Cable while we ride.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Heave out the
<note n="(l)" place="margin">Po. <hi>Lord</hi>
                     </note> heavyeſt of the ware,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let ilka Merchant bear a ſhare.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Set up the Glaſs, Watch turn about,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For of our ſafety I make doubt;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And clear the Boat my Lads with ſpeed,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I fear 'twill be our laſt remeed.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Our Maiſter to his Cabin went,</l>
               <l>And teuk a dram, for he was faint:</l>
               <l>O then a Mountain-Sea came on us!</l>
               <l>And nought ſae ſare cou'd have undone us.</l>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:98884:44"/>
               <l>It broke our Cable, our Boat it ſtav'd,</l>
               <l>Nae lik'ly-heud we cou'd be ſav'd;</l>
               <l>It took ſome Men quite off the Deck,</l>
               <l>And Sprong an ugly fearfow Leck.</l>
               <l>Our ready Carpenters made hye,</l>
               <l>And ſtop't it ſunckat preſently.</l>
               <l>Yet baith our Pumps were right ſare pinch't</l>
               <l>To keep her up, tho we nev'r flinch't.</l>
               <l>A couple of Knights
<note n="(m)" place="margin">County of <hi>Durham,</hi>
                  </note> in this ſame County,</l>
               <l>Wha neither ſpar'd for Pains nor Bounty,</l>
               <l>Clamm up the Shrouds, and wrought
<note n="(n)" place="margin">very heartily,</note> han-ſpan,</l>
               <l>And preuv'd themſel's twa clifty Men;</l>
               <l>Some Neighbours ſhew'd them ſmall regard,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But Virtue is its awn Reward.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Some ſigh'd, and ſome did curſe and damn,</l>
               <l>Some cry'd—<hi>Let's take the tother dram:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Some ſcarch't their Conſciences, and vow'd</l>
               <l>And yelp't for Mercy what they cou'd;</l>
               <l>And ſike a
<note n="(o)" place="margin">diſorderly noiſe</note> Hubby-ſhew was keep't;</l>
               <l>Wou'd wak'ned <hi>Neptune,</hi> had he ſleep't.</l>
               <l>When we with labour were juſt ſpent,</l>
               <l>At laſt we to our Prayers went.</l>
               <l>For Sailors
<note n="(p)" place="margin">ſeldom</note> ſeindle pray, but when</l>
               <l>There is nae help fra Mortal Men;</l>
               <l>Perceiving nae other remeed,</l>
               <l>They pray to God.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>So had they need.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>The Godleſs gang I nam'd before,</l>
               <l>Pelted us off the Weather Shoar:</l>
               <l>They had ſome
<note n="(q)" place="margin">ſcurrilous Libels</note> Cannon on their Ground,</l>
               <l>But thanks to God, they were no' ſound.</l>
               <l>They rattled on, and keep't a buſtle,</l>
               <l>About our Luggs they did ſae whiſtle,</l>
               <l>For aw their
<note n="(r)" place="margin">needleſs ſtir,</note> Dirdom, and their Dinn,</l>
               <l>It was but little they did winn.</l>
               <l>We had a-board an <hi>Obſervator,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Experienc'd at Land and Water:</l>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:98884:44"/>
               <l>He minds the Compaſs and the Tide,</l>
               <l>How the Wind blew, and aw beſide.</l>
               <l>Their Plots and Intrigues cloſely hunted,</l>
               <l>And as they planted he diſmounted.</l>
               <l>They blirted, ſquirted, flirted fondly,</l>
               <l>He Clapper-claw'd their Jerkins ſoundly.</l>
               <l>They preſently ſpent aw their Powder,</l>
               <l>But he repeats louder and louder.</l>
               <l>Says Lown of theirs, <hi>my Joes I fear</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Yon is a parliſh Ingeneer:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Had we him yance out of the way,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They cou'd no' find us ſike tough play.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Perceiving that, he thought it Folly,</l>
               <l>To ſet his breaſt againſt their Volly.</l>
               <l>His down-caſt was their hail intent,</l>
               <l>They aw diſcharge with free Conſent,</l>
               <l>He jowk't, and o'er his head it went.</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Heraclitus</hi> girn'd and laught,</l>
               <l>Whilk ſet the raging Rabble daft;</l>
               <l>They, when their high attempting fails,</l>
               <l>Sneak't off like Dogs had burnt their Tails.</l>
               <l>Our Maiſter inſtantly ſtarts up</l>
               <l>And wiſhfully look't o're the Poop.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Brave Lads, let not your Courage fail,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For thanks to God our
<note n="*" place="margin">The Law ſtill in it's right courſe.</note> Ruther's hail.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mair Comfort for us yet beſide,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For now puts in a high Spring Tide.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The wind which had ſae boiſt'rous blow'n,</l>
               <l>Now by degrees began to Low'n.</l>
               <l>We found our Anchor by the Buoy,</l>
               <l>And wey'd it up with ſmall annoy.</l>
               <l>We hoiſt our Main-ſail gently up,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> out the Water ilka ſup.</l>
               <l>At laſt we got her to a Port,</l>
               <l>Where Weather-beaten Ships reſort.</l>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:98884:45"/>
               <l>My skilfull Pilots, and wiſe Seamen,</l>
               <l>Geud Carpenters, and ſike as thea men,</l>
               <l>She coſt God knaws a deal in Rigging,</l>
               <l>(And ſundry Merchants ran a Begging)</l>
               <l>We rigg'd her up fra Stemm to Stern,</l>
               <l>Securing where ſhe had tane harm;</l>
               <l>Made her, what ever ſhe did ail,</l>
               <l>As tite a Ship as ev'r ſet ſail:</l>
               <l>There's not a Veſſel on the Main,</l>
               <l>But lo'ers to her; <hi>God's haly Name</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Be glorified for the ſame.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Our Maiſter then a-ſhore did ſet me,</l>
               <l>You Lown, ſaid he, I'll ne'er forget ye,</l>
               <l>And with his Foot he kick't my tail</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gang hame,—be Hang'd—and handle your flail.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If ev'r hereafter any ſee me,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">Medling</note> Melling wi' what
<note n="(b)" place="margin">belongs</note> perteens no' to me,</l>
               <l>I'll give him leave (mark what I ſay)</l>
               <l>To hew this Craig of mine: in twa,</l>
               <l>Some of our Lads b'ing very kind,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">At a diſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</note> Alantom follow'd me behind,</l>
               <l>We took a Houſe, where we refreſh't</l>
               <l>Our ſel's wi' what our Hoſteſs fetch't.</l>
               <l>Without, within, we ſoon grew warm,</l>
               <l>A Sang, ſay yane, will do nae harm:</l>
               <l>He lilted up, and ſtraik't his beard,</l>
               <l>An' pleaſe your Worſhip ye ſhall hear't.</l>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap> An, ta, ra, ſounds the tow'ring Trumpets, hah, hah, hah, boo, boo, boo, roars the thund'ring Cannons, for the <hi>James</hi> now. Haſt lads, haſt,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:98884:45"/> up, hang out the Flags, and then Carouſe; yonder <hi>Neptune</hi> wades, he's lea╌ding the Mirmaids, they hear this joyful News. Whip, skip, trip, goes the dancing Dolphins, nev'r tire yet, ſire, ſire now for the Royal <hi>Mary,</hi> boo, boo, boo: Fight Lads, fight, to maintain the Right of brave <hi>James</hi> now. Great Sir! what we can do, will ne're make ſtraight with you; fire, boo, boo, boo, boo, boo, boo. Ho Ship, ho! what Port bound ye to, and whence came you: Lo'er, lo'er here, it's the <hi>Royal Cath'rine</hi> come from <hi>Algier:</hi> She's deep fraught, with re╌dee╌med Chriſtians hither brought; none are left behind, fire, God ſend you fair Wind; fire, beat Drums, ſound a╌loft.</p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:98884:46"/>
               <l>I'll down and ſee the
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Horſe and Mares</note> Yauds well fed,</l>
               <l>It's mair nor time ye were in bed.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>No, call my Groom, inquire of him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>For Hoſtlers for maiſt pairt are ſlim.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enters the</hi> Land-lady <hi>of the Inn.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>L. lady.</speaker>
               <l>Sir, when you pleaſe your Chamber's ready.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>Ay, by and by; ſit down <hi>Land-lady.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This Loyal Health once more I'll drink,</l>
               <l>You'll pledge me heartily I think.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>L. lady.</speaker>
               <l>Ay Sir, I will—pray hold—a Sup</l>
               <l>Is full as good as the whole Cup;</l>
               <l>For Women muſt not be o'erſeen.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">To the <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pant.</hi>
                  </note> Here Friend, God bleſs both King and Queen.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>Come <hi>Land lady</hi>—But what d'ye ſay?</l>
               <l>Will ye not ſing a Verſe or twa?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>L. lady.</speaker>
               <l>As heartily as ev'r I may,</l>
               <l>Becauſe it's Coronation-day.</l>
            </sp>
            <lg>
               <head>I.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap> Right <hi>Titan,</hi> when from watry Bed,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap> has freſh Career, begun;</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap> begs leave to dry his moiſty Head,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap> at <hi>Britain</hi>'s Beaming Sun:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap> He can╌not in╌flu╌ence the Flocks,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap> nor make the Meads look green;</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="music">
                     <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                  </gap> 'till he combs out his Lankey-Locks, before our Radiant Queen.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:98884:46"/>
            <lg>
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>What makes the new blown Roſe creep in</l>
               <l>And dares not ſhew it's Face?</l>
               <l>But makes the ſweeteſt Flowers begin</l>
               <l>To fly with flighteſt pace?</l>
               <l>What makes the Tulip caſt it's Leaves?</l>
               <l>Not let them here be ſeen?</l>
               <l>They muſt not touch, the ſight's too much</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Britains</hi> Beauteous Queen.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>III.</head>
               <l>What make the lofty Cedar droop,</l>
               <l>As if not well at eaſe?</l>
               <l>What makes the neighb'ring Foreſts ſtoop,</l>
               <l>As all were Shrubs, no Trees?</l>
               <l>Like Noon-day-Owls, they hide their Boles,</l>
               <l>Their timber is but mean,</l>
               <l>The Royal-Oak, without a ſtroak,</l>
               <l>Will Conquer for our Queen.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>IV.</head>
               <l>What makes <hi>Diana</hi> court the ſhades?</l>
               <l>What makes her Nymphs recoil?</l>
               <l>A Chaſter Beauty them invades,</l>
               <l>They're proud they've got the Foil:</l>
               <l>Her Prieſts need keep no holy-day,</l>
               <l>No Off'rings as have been;</l>
               <l>Nor Sacrifice but to the eyes</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Britains</hi> Goddeſs Queen.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>V.</head>
               <l>From whence hear I thoſe chearful Chirps?</l>
               <l>Ev'n from her Sacred Feet;</l>
               <l>The Moans, the Groans of needy ones,</l>
               <l>Are turn'd to Muſick ſweet:</l>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:98884:47"/>
               <l>Why no Complaints from Indigents?</l>
               <l>What makes the Goals ſo thinn?</l>
               <l>The Bounty, and the Charity,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Britains</hi> pious Queen.</l>
            </lg>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ten.</speaker>
               <l>Well ſung dear Hoſteſs, come my Dow,</l>
               <l>And let me kiſs that
<note n="(a)" place="margin">well-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd Mouth.</note> weel-fourd mow,</l>
               <l>When <hi>awld Megg</hi> dy's then have at you.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Land.</speaker>
               <l>Th' enamel'd Flower ſpreads its imbelliſh'd Leaves,</l>
               <l>Gives thanks for what 't has got, and more receives;</l>
               <l>But haughty Rebels dare all Rights deny,</l>
               <l>And God, and his Anointed both defie!</l>
               <l>Oh! wretch'd Ingratitude! not to regard,</l>
               <l>Their Sov'raigns good Example,
<note place="margin">A good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject cannot make an ill Prince.</note> nor Reward!</l>
               <l>As if the Almighty only did Create</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Kings</hi> for the <hi>Objects</hi> of their <hi>Subjects</hi> Hate,</l>
               <l>Not to be Honour'd, but be ſpurned at.</l>
               <l>We'll talk no more, I think we'ad beſt</l>
               <l>Go ſay our Pray'rs, and ſo to reſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:98884:47"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of ſome Books, Printed for <hi>Benjamin Tooke,</hi> at the <hi>Ship</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-Yard.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <head>FOLIO.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>HErodoti Halicarnaſſaei Hiſtoriaram Libri</hi> 9. <hi>Greek and Latin.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Franciſci Suarez Tractatus de Legibus ac Deo Legiſlatore.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Works of the moſt Reverend Father in God <hi>John Bramhall,</hi> D. D. late Lord Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Ardmagh,</hi> Primate and Metropolitan of all <hi>Ireland,</hi> with his Life:</item>
               <item>A Collection of all the Statutes now in force in the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Richard Baker</hi>'s Chronicle of the Kings of <hi>England.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Littleton</hi>'s Sermons.</item>
               <item>Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon</hi>'s Sermons.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Hum. Winch</hi>'s Book of Entries.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>M. T. Ciceronis Opera omnia decem Indicibus,</hi> 2. <hi>Vol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Skinneri Etymologicon Linguae Anglicanae.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Heylyn</hi>'s Coſmography in 4. Books.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Math. Paris, Hiſtoria Anglia.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr <hi>Nalſons</hi> Collections from the begining of the late Rebellion to the Murther of of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, 2 Vol.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Heraclitus Ridens,</hi> or a Dialogue between <hi>Jeſt</hi> and <hi>Earneſt</hi> concerning the Times.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh</hi>'s Hiſtory of the World.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Brown</hi>'s Travels through divers parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> as <hi>Germany, Hungary,</hi> &amp;c. Wherein are Deſcriptions of the moſt important places, in the preſent War; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Emperor, and the Grand Scignior; Illuſtrated with Sculptures.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>N. Lloydii Dictionarium Geographico-Poeticum, Edit.</hi> 2.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>QUARTO.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Phocena,</hi> or the Anatomy of a <hi>Porpeſs,</hi> diſſected at <hi>Greſham</hi> Colledg; by <hi>Edw. Tyſon,</hi> M.D.</item>
               <item>Separation of the Churches from Epiſcopal Government, as Practiſed by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Nonconformiſts, proved Schiſmatical, by <hi>Henry Dodwell,</hi> A.M.</item>
               <item>The Beauty of Unity, in a Sermon Preached at <hi>Preſton,</hi> by <hi>Rich. Wroe;</hi> D.D.</item>
               <item>The Vanity of the Diſſenters Plea, for their Separation; a Sermon preached be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King at <hi>Windſor,</hi> by <hi>Rob. Creighton,</hi> D. D.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:98884:48"/>
               <item>Of Perjury, a Sermon Preached at the Aſſizes at <hi>Cheſter,</hi> by <hi>John Allen,</hi> M. A. Fellow of Trinity Colledg in <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Sermon Preached before the Honorable Houſe of Commons, <hi>November</hi> the 5th. by <hi>Henry Dove,</hi> D. D.</item>
               <item>A Sermon Preached, before the Lord Mayor of the City of <hi>London,</hi> on the Feaſt of St. <hi>Michael,</hi> by <hi>Henry Dove.</hi> D. D.</item>
               <item>A Sermon Preached before the King at <hi>White Hall,</hi> on the Feaſt of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, by <hi>Henry Dove,</hi> D. D. Publiſhed by his late Majeſties ſpecial Command.</item>
               <item>The preſent Miſeries and Miſchiefs of Sin, diſcourſed in a Sermon, before the Lord Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> by <hi>Robert Wenſely</hi> Vicar of <hi>Cheſthunt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ferguſon</hi>'s Text explained, and applyed, in a Sermon before the Lord Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> by <hi>Robert Wenſely,</hi> Vicar of <hi>Cheſthunt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Oratio Anniverſaria habita in Theatro Coll. Med. Lond. a Georgio Rogers, ejuſdem Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legii Socio.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Collection of Caſes and other Diſcourſes, lately written to recover Diſſenters to the Communion of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> by ſome Divines of the City of <hi>London,</hi> 2 Volumes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cauſae Veteris Epitaphium, accedit cauſa vetus conclamata.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Concavum Cappo-cloacorum,</hi> or a View in little, contained under a brace of Caps.</item>
               <item>A Sermon preached at the Funeral of Sir <hi>Roger Bradſhaigh,</hi> Knight and Baronet, by <hi>Richard Wroe,</hi> D. D.</item>
               <item>A Sermon Preached before the King at <hi>Wincheſter, September</hi> 9. 1681. By <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Turner,</hi> D. D. Dean of <hi>Windſor.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Sermon Preached before the Lord Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> on <hi>Eaſter Monday,</hi> 1684. by <hi>Francis</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Sermon Preached before the King at <hi>White-Hall, November</hi> 5. 1684. By <hi>Francis</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Ely,</hi> and Almoner to the King.</item>
               <item>The Books of the Old Teſtament, tranſlated into <hi>Iriſh,</hi> by the care and diligence of Dr. <hi>W. Bedle,</hi> late Biſhop of <hi>Kilmore.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The New Teſtament of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> tranſlated into <hi>Iriſh,</hi> both Printed in the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Character.</item>
               <item>The True Widdow, a Comedy, by <hi>Tho. Shadwell.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Works of the Reverend, and Learned Mr. <hi>John Gregory,</hi> M. A. of <hi>Chriſt</hi>-Church in <hi>Oxon,</hi> in two parts.</item>
               <item>A Brief Account of Ancient Church Government, with a Reflection on ſeveral Modern Writers of the Presbyterians.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ogygia, ſeu rerum Hibernicarum Chronologia; ex pervetus tis Monumentis fideliter inter ſe collat is eruta, atque ex ſacris ac prophanis literis primarum orbis gentium, tum Genealo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicis quam Chronologicis ſufflaminata praeſidijs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Cum Catalogo Regum in Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tannia Scotorum. Authore Roderico O Flaherto, Armig.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:98884:48"/>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi>OCTAVO</hi> and <hi>TWELVES.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>TWO Letters of Advice. 1. for the Suſception of Holy Orders. 2. for <hi>Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies Theological,</hi> with a Catalogue of the Chriſtian Writers, and genuinne Writers, that are extant of the firſt 3 Centuries, 80.</item>
               <item>Some Conſiderations of preſent concernment, how far <hi>Romaniſts</hi> may be truſted by Princes of another Perſwaſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 80.</item>
               <item>A Reply to Mr. <hi>Baxter's</hi> pretended Confutation of a Book, Intituled, Separation of Churches, from Epiſcopal Government, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 80.</item>
               <item>A Diſcourſe concerning the One Altar, and the One Prieſthood, inſiſted on by the Ancients, in their diſputes againſt Schiſm, 80.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Diſſertationes Cyprianicae,</hi> 80.</item>
               <item>Two ſhort Diſcourſes againſt the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> 120.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>H. Grotii de Caenae Adminiſtratione, ubi Paſtores non ſunt, diſſertatio, cum diverſorum reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponſionibus,</hi> 80. Theſe ſeven written by <hi>Henry Dodwel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> M. A.</item>
               <item>Navigation and Commerce, their Original and Progreſs, by <hi>J. Evelyn</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> 80.</item>
               <item>Of Gifts and Offices in the Publick Worſhip of God, in 3 parts, by <hi>Edw. Weten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall,</hi> D. D. Lord Biſhop of <hi>Cork,</hi> 80.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Clavis Aſtrologiae Elimata:</hi> Or a Key to the whole Art of Aſtrology, new Filed and Poliſhed, in 3 parts; the Second Edition enlarged, by <hi>Henry Coley,</hi> Student in the Mathematicks and Aſtrology.</item>
               <item>The Holy Life of Monſieur <hi>de Rently,</hi> a late Noble man of <hi>France,</hi> 80.</item>
               <item>A Proſpect of the State of <hi>Ireland,</hi> by <hi>P. W.</hi> 80.</item>
               <item>The Experienced Angler, or Angling Improved, by Coll. <hi>Venables.</hi> 80.</item>
               <item>The Sceptical Chymiſt, by <hi>Rob. Boyle,</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
               </item>
               <item>The Degrees of Conſanguinity and Aſſinity, by <hi>R. Dixon,</hi> D. D.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Elenchus Antiquitatum Alibonenſium, per Dan. Langhern, S. T. B.</hi> 80.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chronicon Regum Anglorum ab Hengiſto uſque ad Heptarchiaefinem, per Dan. Langhorn,</hi> 80.</item>
               <item>Poems and Songs, by <hi>Tho. Flatman,</hi> 80. The fourth Edition.</item>
               <item>Poems Written on ſeveral Occaſions, by <hi>N. Tote,</hi> the ſecond Edition.</item>
               <item>The <hi>French</hi> Gardiner, out of <hi>French</hi> by <hi>J Evelyn,</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> 80.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Alaxiae Obſtaoulum,</hi> 80.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gardinerus de Trinitate cortra Sandium,</hi> 80.</item>
               <item>The Catechiſm of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> with Marginal Notes, by <hi>Edw. Weten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall,</hi> D. D. Lord Biſhop of <hi>Cork.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Phaedri Fabulae ex recenſione Chr. Waſe,</hi> 80.</item>
               <item>The Country Parſon's Advice to his Pariſhioners, 80.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Des Cartes</hi>'s Metaphyſical Meditations, with his Life, by <hi>W. Molyneaux,</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> 80.</item>
               <item>The Life of the Biſhop of <hi>Munſter,</hi> 80.</item>
               <item>The <hi>Aerial Noctiluca,</hi> by <hi>R. Boyle,</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> 80.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:98884:49"/>
               <item>New Experiments and Obſervations made upon the <hi>Icy Noctiluca,</hi> by <hi>R. Boyle,</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> 80. <hi>Idem.</hi> in Latin, 120.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thealma &amp; Clearchus,</hi> a Paſtoral Hiſtory, 80.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gocperi Grammatica Linguae Anglieanae,</hi> 80.</item>
               <item>Vulgar Errors in Divinity removed, 80.</item>
               <item>A Manual of Examples for School Exerciſe, 80.</item>
               <item>Of the ſubject of Church Power in whom it reſides, by <hi>Simon Lowth,</hi> Vicar of <hi>Coſmus Blent,</hi> 80.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dictionarium Trilingue ſecundum locos Communes nommibus uſitatioribus Anglis, Latinis, Graecis, Opera. I. Raii M. A. S. R. L.</hi> 80.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Henry Wotton</hi>'s Remains, 80.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Herbert</hi>'s Country Parſon, 120.</item>
               <item>The Form of Soundwords by <hi>R. Wenſley,</hi> Vicar of <hi>Cheſthut,</hi> 120.</item>
               <item>An Enquiry into the Miniſtry of the Presbyterians, 120.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Aero Chaimos;</hi> or a Regiſter for the Air, by <hi>N. Henſhaw,</hi> M. D.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lingard's</hi> Letter of Advice to a young Gentleman leaving the Univerſity, 120.</item>
               <item>The Souldiers Guide, being an Eſſay offer'd to all of that Profeſſion, 120.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:98884:49"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
